<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Faithfull searching home vvord, intended for the view of the remaining members of the former old Parliament in the time of their late second sitting at Westminster. Shewing the reasonableness and justness of their first dissolution, as also the dangerous rock they formerly split upon, that so they might learn to beware for the future: But being a second time dissolved upon the like account, as so many fruitless trees twic dead plucked up by the roots. It is now presented to the officers of the army as another looking-glass wherein they may plainly see, how woefully they also have dissembled, dealt treacherously, deceitfully and wickedly both with God and man, in having so greatly apostatized from, rejected, trodden under foot, persecuted, Judas-like betrayed, and as it were crucified and kept down in the grave (as the soldiers formerly did Christ) that blessed cause and those good principles, they once so highly pretended to own ... Together with an other seasonable word by way of counsel and proposal to the aforesaid officers of the armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland. All which, is also to be seen, and read of all men loving righteousness, that thereby they may (with the army) better know how to chuse the good, refute the evil, and rightly steer their course, and bend their spirits in the future, for the exaltation of Christ, his cause, and interest, and against all the apostacy and treachery, though never so refined, that may further appear in this gloomy, dark, overturning day.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E774_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207286</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50796677</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50796677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 118:E774[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Faithfull searching home vvord, intended for the view of the remaining members of the former old Parliament in the time of their late second sitting at Westminster. Shewing the reasonableness and justness of their first dissolution, as also the dangerous rock they formerly split upon, that so they might learn to beware for the future: But being a second time dissolved upon the like account, as so many fruitless trees twic dead plucked up by the roots. It is now presented to the officers of the army as another looking-glass wherein they may plainly see, how woefully they also have dissembled, dealt treacherously, deceitfully and wickedly both with God and man, in having so greatly apostatized from, rejected, trodden under foot, persecuted, Judas-like betrayed, and as it were crucified and kept down in the grave (as the soldiers formerly did Christ) that blessed cause and those good principles, they once so highly pretended to own ... Together with an other seasonable word by way of counsel and proposal to the aforesaid officers of the armies of England, Scotland, and Ireland. All which, is also to be seen, and read of all men loving righteousness, that thereby they may (with the army) better know how to chuse the good, refute the evil, and rightly steer their course, and bend their spirits in the future, for the exaltation of Christ, his cause, and interest, and against all the apostacy and treachery, though never so refined, that may further appear in this gloomy, dark, overturning day.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the first year of the army's endeavouring to deal treacherously with the faithful friends of the cause a second time, after their first and second dissolution of the late long Parliament, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Faithfull Searching HOME WORD, Intended for the view of the remaining Members of the former OLD PARLIAMENT In the time of their late ſecond Sitting at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING The Reaſonableneſs and Juſtneſs of their firſt Diſſolution, as alſo the dangerous Rocks they formerly ſplit upon, that ſo they might learn to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware for the future: But being a ſecond time Diſſolved upon the like Account, as ſo many Fruitleſs Trees <hi>twice Dead plucked up by the Roots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is now preſented to the Officers of the Army as another <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> wherein they may plainly ſee, how wofully they alſo have <hi>Diſſembled, Dealt Treacherouſly,</hi> Deceitfully and Wickedly both with God and Man, in having ſo greatly <hi>Apoſtatized from, Rejected, Trodden under foot, Perſecuted, Judas-like Betrayed,</hi> and as it were <hi>Crucified</hi> and kept down in the Grave (as the <hi>Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> formerly did Chriſt) that Bleſſed <hi>Cauſe</hi> and thoſe Good <hi>Principles,</hi> they once ſo highly pretended to own; and have done the ſame, yea worſe things themſelves, then for which the late King was Beheaded, and they pretendedly Diſſolved the late Old Parliament, a firſt and ſecond time; and have been <hi>Pharaoh, Edom,</hi> and <hi>Moab</hi>-like, the onely main Hinderers of the Lords Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full People from going to <hi>Zion,</hi> which hath ſo pulled down the late and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Judgements which have been and yet are lying upon theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>Together with another Seaſonable Word by way of Counſel and Propoſal to the aforeſaid Officers of the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which, is alſo to be ſeen, and read of all men loving Righteouſneſs, that thereby they may (with the Army) the better know how to <hi>chuſe the Good,</hi> refuſe the Evil, and rightly ſteer their Courſe, and bend their Spirits in the future, for the Exaltation of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and againſt all the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Treachery,</hi> though never ſo refined, that may further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this <hi>Gloomy, Dark, Overturning Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 24.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>From the utmoſt parts of the Earth have we heard Songs, even Glory to the Righteous: But I ſaid, My leanneſs, my leanneſs, woe unto me, the Treacherous Dealers <hi>[to wit, the late Old Parliament]</hi> have dealt treacherouſly: Yea the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Dealers <hi>[viz. the Officers of the Army]</hi> have dealt very treacherouſly.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the firſt Year of the Army's endeavouring to deal treacherouſly with the Faithful Friends of the Cauſe a ſecond time, after their firſt and ſecond Diſſolution of the late long Parliament, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:167283:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:167283:2"/>
            <head>A Faithful Searching Home Word, intended for the view of the remaining Members of the former Long Parliament, in the time of their late Second Sitting at <hi>VVeſtminſter;</hi> ſhewing the Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Juſtneſs of their firſt Diſſolution, as alſo the dangerous Rocks they formerly ſplit upon; that ſo they might learn to beware for the future, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>YOu may remember, when in the day of your former ſitting as the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>Repreſentors,</hi> and a faithful Party among you, were according to their then light going on in the Lords work taking away the <hi>Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Antichriſtian,</hi> heavy <hi>Yokes,</hi> which the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Prelates,</hi> laid upon the <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the good people of this Nation, and alſo the Army, together with your ſelves, gave them hopes, that you would endeavour to take away all the remaining Oppreſſions that then were, or in the future ſhould be found lying upon them, and would bring forth Righteouſneſs to them (as by many Declarations may appear) which was then, hath been all along, yet is, and in every Generation for time to come, (but above all when the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall moſt viſibly appear, and be ſet up in the world) will be the Cauſe of God and his People; that by the good Providence of the Lord, as alſo through the many <hi>Prayers, Petitions,</hi> and <hi>Strivings</hi> of the <hi>honeſt Party</hi> in the <hi>Nation, Army,</hi> and among <hi>your Selves,</hi> to, and with the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> and againſt the common enemy, very great and wonderful things were ſucceſſively one time after another brought about, and done amongſt us, towards the eaſe of the people; <hi>viz.</hi> the late King brought to Juſtice, and other great ones with him, his <hi>Monarchy, Houſe of Lords,</hi> together with his own, and the aforeſaid Tyranny of his <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> (ſo called) and of other corrupt perſons, with much of the Oppreſſion then lying upon us, taken away; How the Lord bleſt you with ſucceſs in your <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Forces</hi> both by <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Sea,</hi> and you alſo had the love and prayers of the good people, and what a terrour of you was upon the Enemy both at home and abroad, whileſt ſome who were faithful among You, and the honeſt part of the Army, were in the zealous proſecution of theſe things, and afterwards declared for the Deſtruction of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and appeared to be growing up into the <hi>Light, Spirit,</hi> and were doing the <hi>things</hi> relating and leading thereunto, you very well know.</p>
            <p>The Enemy being every where totally ſubdued, and the three Nations of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with all the Territories thereunto belonging in our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167283:3"/>hands; the <hi>Dutch Fleet</hi> alſo beaten at ſea, and they thereby almoſt brought as it were upon their knees, in the doing whereof, the appearances and ſalvation of the Lord with, and about his poor unworthy people, were ſo very wonderful and glorious, that the <hi>faith</hi> and expectations of many or moſt of them who went along with him to that day (eſpecially towards the latter end) whrleſt theſe things were doing, were very much raiſed, and that from Scripture grounds to be eying the <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Propheſies</hi> relating to <hi>the Deliverance of Zion; The Deſtruction of Babylon and Antichriſt; The Call of the Jews; The Advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> all which ſhall certainly be fulfilled in the latter dayes. (Among other ſee the following Scriptures. Firſt, <hi>The deliverance of Zion, Pſal.</hi> 48. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.35, 36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13. to 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13. to the end, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5, 6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.9, 10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.3, 5. to 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4, 8, 9, 11, 12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.19, 21. to 25. <hi>Micha.</hi> 4.2, 3, 4, 10. to 13. <hi>Obadiah verſe</hi> 17, 18, 21. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.13, 15, 17. to 20. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.7. to 13. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.3. to 8. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.15, 16. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.2, 3, 4. to 9. Secondly, <hi>The Deſtruction of Babylon and Antichriſt, Iſa.</hi> 47. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. Thirdly, <hi>The Call of the Jews, Jer.</hi> 23.3, 7, 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.3, 10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.8, 9, 11, 12.23.28. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.24. to the end. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21, 22. <hi>Amos</hi> 9.14, 15. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.20. to the end. Fourthly, <hi>The Kingdom of Chriſt, Pſal.</hi> 72.1, 8. to 17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.15, 16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.24, 25. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14, 27. <hi>Obadiah verſe</hi> 21. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9, 10. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32, 33. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. <hi>John</hi> 18.37. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14, 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26, 27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.27. And that theſe Scriptures ſhall certainly be fulfilled, ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 33, 20, 21, 25, 26. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.22. <hi>I the Lord will haſten it in his time.</hi>) And could believe no other, but that thoſe late wonderfull Revolutions and Overturnings, did loudly call upon them to be looking out that way, and to be conſidering what was next to be done by them, in order to a further going on with the Lord as Inſtruments of his pleaſure, in the bringing forth theſe things.</p>
            <p>And knowing very well that the Lord eminently owned his people, and his preſence was wonderfully with them whileſt there was a zealous preſſing after Righteouſneſs, and ſtrong endeavours uſed by ſome among you, and in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to get the moſt <hi>godly, faithful</hi> men into all places of <hi>Truſt,</hi> in the <hi>Army, Navy,</hi> and elſewhere, who would <hi>brow beat</hi> and <hi>puniſh wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and endeavour to promote <hi>goodneſs,</hi> and good men, and that nothing proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd and went on to purpoſe till this bleſſed courſe and way was taken. (Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Victory obtained by the Eaſtern Aſſociation Sectarian (ſo called) Horſemen (chiefly) and Foot at <hi>Marſton Moor,</hi> againſt <hi>Prince Rupert,</hi> and his Army; Alſo (after the <hi>New Moddel</hi>) at <hi>Naſeby Fight,</hi> Afterwards in the <hi>Weſt;</hi> Then at <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>Lanckaſhire</hi> againſt <hi>Duke Hamilton</hi> and the <hi>Scottiſh Army;</hi> The ſubduing of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> The <hi>Fleet</hi> alſo beating the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and ſo on till the laſt Battel at <hi>Worceſter.</hi>) They were very much carried forth to deſire, and endeavour that all things for the future might run in that channel; without
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167283:3"/>which, they were conſidently perſwaded (as well they might) that the Lords for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer preſence would not be with our <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Forces,</hi> as it was before but would forſake them.</p>
            <p>Now there being at that time a Corrupt, Malignant, Neutral, Presbyterian party among you in the Houſe, as there hath been all along, and was to the very day of your Second Diſſolution, who were unſuitable to the work you were called to do, and that knew not<note n="*" place="margin">Let the Army beware of this.</note> 
               <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but rather cloſed with wicked men and enemies, they did ſo oppoſe and hinder, that the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and Juſtice, and putting faithful men into places of <hi>Truſt,</hi> ſo greatly deſired, and promiſed, could not be effected as it ought to be: Inſomuch, that when the late <hi>General Cromwel</hi> came from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſeveral perſons eminent for Godlineſs of the <hi>Congregations</hi> in, and about <hi>London,</hi> and others, came to him, <hi>Deſiring that he would employ his utmoſt endeavours to get you to improve the great Mercies and Victories which the Lord had beſtowed upon us, as alſo to anſwer the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of his people in doing the good things promiſed.</hi> In anſwer to which he replied, (beſide other as bad expreſſions of you) That <hi>there was no more hopes of drawing on the Parliament thereunto,</hi> [meaning you] <hi>then was of making a bar of iron become a Lute ſtring;</hi> and deſired, <hi>that they with the Congregations to which they did relate, would ſeek unto the Lord to know his pleaſure, in what was to be done, and to let him know what upon ſuch ſeeking ſhould be ſet upon their hearts;</hi> whereof you ſhall hear more afterward. And would likewiſe ſay of you at other times, that <hi>there was not above five or ſix of you in the Houſe</hi> [which more plainly appeared in your ſecond ſitting] <hi>that had either a heart or minde to do any good thing,</hi> which words were oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by ſeveral other good people who came to him for help, complaining, That <hi>they had waited upon you day after day till their hearts aked, their legs were weary and they almoſt undone, and could get little or nothing from you but a company of fair promiſes.</hi> Others ſaying, <hi>That when you did any thing for them, it was for the moſt part ſo long firſt, that they had almoſt as good have been without it.</hi> And was it not too much ſo in your ſecond ſitting.</p>
            <p>Many alſo were the complaints of the Countrey people and others againſt you upon the ſame account; ſome of them ſaying, <hi>That you were a company of corrupt ſelf-ſeeking perſons, that minded your own Intereſt more then any thing elſe, which</hi> [they ſaid] <hi>was manifeſted by giving and receiving gifts, to and from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the Spoils of the Enemy, that ought to have been brought into the Lords Treaſury for the diſcharging of Publick Debts, and the further carrying on of his work withall: And that you preferr'd your Kindred, Relations, Friends, Servants, and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, whether wiſe men or fools, honeſt men or knaves, into places of Truſt,</hi> [and ſo it was in your ſecond ſitting, witneſs <hi>Nedham</hi> and others] <hi>contrary to the Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſo much pretended to in that day; wherefore you being acted by ſuch a corrupt ſelf-ſeeking ſpirit, little or no good at all could be expected from you.</hi> All which being too ſadly known to the forementioned good people of the ſeveral Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they propoſed to the General, &amp;c. (as being the reſult of what was ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their hearts after ſeeking the Lord.) <hi>That a ſhort time of ſix moneths or thereabouts might be put to your ſitting, and that in the interim care might be taken for the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167283:4"/>of perſons to be elected to ſucceed in the Government which might be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord for the further carrying on of his work, which you had not enough of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Were you not as ſhort of ſpirit for the work in your ſecond ſitting as before.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit</hi> [nor it ſeems of honeſty] <hi>to go on in withal.</hi> And to ſay the truth, upon this account, among other the like things that might be mentioned, was there a general out-cry amongſt moſt of the friends of the Cauſe in the three Nations for a New <hi>Repreſentative</hi> (as ſo called in that day) and for your Diſſolution; the <hi>Generall</hi> (as you have heard) by himſelf, together with the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> as well as others, complaining of you, and both private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and publiquely, among themſelves, and elſewhere, breathing out their deſires for your Diſſolution, and that ſuch faithful perſons might come into the <hi>Power,</hi> as would indeed bring forth the good things promiſed, as may more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, in a Letter ſent by the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Lieutenant General Fleetwood</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> after you were diſſolved, ſhewing the reaſons thereof, ſigned by <hi>Major General Lambert, Major Generall Disbrow, Commiſſary Generall Whaly, Major General Harriſon, Collonel Saunders, Collonel Hacker, Collonel Rich, Captain Farley, Major Packer, Major Wiggan, and others.</hi> As alſo in a Speech made by <hi>General Cromwel</hi> in his own, and in the names of the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> to the Members of the <hi>Little Parliament</hi> in the Council Chamber before their Sitting, likewiſe ſhewing the grounds and neceſſity of their diſſolving you, and by way of encouragement to them to ſit; in both which are ſeveral Particulars laid to your Charge, with which whoſoever ſhall compare your late ſpirit and actions, it will very plainly appear, that you were rather worſe in your late ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſitting, then in the time of your firſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt begin with the<note n="*" place="margin">Both the Letter and Speech may be ſeen in a Book called, <hi>The Fifth Monarchy, or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt in Oppoſition to the Beaſts.</hi> Sold at the Crown in <hi>Popeshead Alley.</hi>
               </note> Letter, wherein are five of the Particulars of your Charge.</p>
            <p>See that Book, page 22. Firſt, <hi>They complain of your evil mannagement of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs that were under your hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the then dangerous remedy of diſſolving you was not uſed till all other ways had been by the Army aſſayed, and by you rejected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That after four years expectation from you, ſince the change of the Government</hi> [to wit from <hi>Kingſhip</hi> to a Commonwealth] <hi>they found no</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Was it not ſo again in this your ſecond ſitting? Indeed you were very expert in laying Burthens and Taxes upon the people. But what Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Juſtice did you bring forth? Or what yokes lying either upon the Conſciences or Bodies of the good people did you take away? Or what hath the Officers of the Army, who thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of you; and diſſolved you for not doing theſe good things, done herein to this very day, but ſtrive to advance and ſettle themſelves.</note> 
               <hi>performance by you of thoſe good things that tended to the ſettlement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in Peace and Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They ſay, <hi>They were abundantly ſatisfied from the long experience they had of you; that as you were then conſtituted, you were ſo far from being the Inſtruments of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:167283:4"/>perfecting the Work of the Lord, that the whole Cauſe was in great danger to periſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your hands, for which there hath been ſo vaſt an expence of Blood and Treaſure; and therefore after ſeeking the face of God, and taking counſel with one another, it was generally apprehended, that the onely way left to preſerve the Cauſe, was to prevent your ſitting by a ſpeedy diſſolving you, and laying the Government upon the ſhoulders of ſuch men as might hopefully give the People the fruit of all their Labour, and Blood, and encourage good men to be ſtill willing to hazard their lives againſt the Common Enemy, which, as things then ſtood, many had little heart to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That it was in their hearts to ſeek thoſe good things in ſuch a way, as that you might have had the honour of it, but you had not then a heart to incline to the Motion made in order thereunto; but rather endeavoured a haſty inconſiderate paſſing of an Act for</hi> a New Repreſentative, <hi>though the General and Officers at a meeting, with many of your Members, did abundantly demonſtrate the evident danger of it: yet did you the next day ſo earneſtly and precipitantly perſiſt in it, as neceſſitated them to put you to that ſuddain diſſolution.</hi> Thus far the Letter.</p>
            <p>They alſo ſay in the Speech by way of charge againſt you, ſee page 29, 30, 31. of the forementioned Book, wherein are twelve Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That when the General and the Officers of the Army came from</hi> Worceſter, <hi>they expected that you having ſuch a Hiſtory to look back unto, a God that appeared for you ſo eminently, ſo viſibly; the mercies that God had ſhewed, the expectations that were in the hearts of all good men, would have prompted you, that were in Authority, to have done thoſe good things, which might, by honeſt men, have been judged a Return fit for ſuch a God, and worthy of ſuch Mercies, and a diſcharge of duty to thoſe for whom all theſe Mercies had been ſhewed,</hi> (to wit) <hi>the true intereſt of the three Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>And likewiſe</hi> ſay,] <hi>They came fully bent in their hearts and thoughts to deſire and uſe all fair and lawful means they could with you, to have had the Nation reap the fruit of all that Blood and Treaſure that had been expended in this Cauſe, and had many thirſtings in their ſpirits, to finde out wayes, and means wherein they might be any wayes inſtrumental to help it forward, and that they did from time to time ſolicite you to that purpoſe; and when they ſaw nothing could be done they reminded you by a Petition, but had no return at all; all the ſatisfaction they could get from you was but a few words. And finding the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It hath ſince appear'd, that the Armies ſtrivings and thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to have had the Nation better'd by all the expence of Blood and Treaſure, hath onely been to greaten and enrich themſelves, and ſtudying how to get the peoples money to be upheld therein, whereby they are looked upon as cheating, ſelf-ſeeking, unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons as well as your ſelves, neither of you both having either honour or repute, but are a ſtink unto all honeſt men; do bring down judgements upon the Nation, put all things into confuſion, yet neither they nor you the honeſty or goodneſs to lay theſe things to heart to this very day, but <hi>Lambert, Disbrow, Berry</hi>-like, go on to advance your ſelves, though the Nation periſh.</note> 
               <hi>diſſatisfied in every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and bringing home to their doors the Non-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe things that had been promiſed, and were of due to be performed, judging themſelves concern'd</hi> (they ſay) <hi>they endevoured, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came honeſt Men, to keep up the Reputation of honeſt men in the world,</hi> [it ſeems you would not] <hi>and therefore had divers times endeavoured to obtain a Meeting with divers of your Members, and in thoſe Meetings did in all faithfulneſs and ſincerity beſeech you, that you would be mindeful of your duty, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167283:5"/>of the diſcharge of your Truſt to God and man, and that they had at the leaſt ten or twelve Meetings begging and beſeeching you, that of your own accords you would do thoſe good things that had been promiſed, that ſo it might appear you did not do them by any ſuggeſtion from the Army, but of your own ingenuities, that ſo you might have the reputation and good opinion of the people to the utmoſt; alſo declared plainly to you, that the Iſſue of not doing thoſe good things would be the judgement and diſpleaſure of God againſt you, the diſſatisfaction of the people, and the putting things into confuſion, yet they could not prevail with you, and that you laid them not to heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That you would not hear of a New Repreſentative till ſuch time as the Army came to their cloſe conſiderations what to do, and then you began to take it to heart, and ſeem'd exceeding willing to put it on, but not with that integrity and caution as would have ſaved the Cauſe and Intereſt that you and they had been ſo long engaged in, and that your intendment and deſign [in all you did at that time] was onely to recruit the Houſe the better to perpetuate your ſelves, ſeveral of the Officers having divers times been ſpoken to by you to give way thereto, which was ſo unreaſonable a thing, as they not onely had a perpetual averſation to, but did abominate the thoughts of, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes declared their diſſatisfaction with and judgements againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That though you were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to hear of a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It was juſt thus with you in your ſecond ſitting; for though you ſeem'd exceeding willing to hear of Propoſalls from the Friends of the Cauſe in order to Settlement, yet your ſpirits too much cloſed with that ſpirit that here they ſo complain'd of, and could not endure to hear of ſuch faithful perſons coming into power, as would indeed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Cauſe; witneſs your late voting <hi>Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Harriſon</hi> uncapable of future employment, &amp;c. and reſolved as formerly to recruit the Houſe with men of the ſame ſpirit as your-ſelves. And therefore no wonder the Army and the good people declare their diſſatisfaction with, and rejoyce in your Diſſolution as before. Yet in this very thing hath the Army done worſe themſelves, as you may ſee afterwards.</note> 
               <hi>New Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative before, or to proceed in one line conſiderable in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had lain three years before you, yet when the Army came to their cloſe conſiderations, inſtead of protracting, you made as much prepoſterous haſte on the other hand to put it on, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration or care had in the Qualifications of the Act, you were about to aſſert and provide for the ſecurity of the Cauſe, but would have thrown it back into the hands of them we firſt fought with, which had they ſuffered you to have done, they ſhould have been rendred the worſt people in the world, and have become Traytors both to God and man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That the Intereſt of the People of God was grown cheap with you, and not laid to heart; a alſo if they came to Competition of things, the Cauſe even among your ſelves, was (even almoſt in every thing) going to the ground, and ſaw plainly and evidently, that in ſome Critical things, the Cauſe of the people of God was a deſpiſed thing: and therefore not yours, but the hands of other men muſt be truſted with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That if any body were in Competition for any place of real and ſignal Truſt, it was a hard and difficult thing to get any thing to be Carried without making parties, without things indeed unworthy of a Parliament, and not as it ought to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:167283:5"/>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That you</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Alderman <hi>Atkins</hi> his ſaying in the <hi>Houſe</hi> in the time of your late ſitting, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Sympſon <hi>was an Anabaptiſt, and would not Chriſten Children, nor give the Sacrament</hi> (as he called it) <hi>to the people;</hi> alſo as ignorantly ſeconded by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He believed the Sacrament was a converting Ordinance, and that the Miniſters of Mr.</hi> Sympſons <hi>judgement were not the Miniſters you intended to own.</hi> With other the like arguments to keep him out of <hi>Biſhopſgate.</hi> As alſo keeping Mr. <hi>Feak</hi> out of <hi>Chriſt Church,</hi> (ſo called) though formerly put in by your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and continuing Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> there, who was formerly ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and impriſoned by you upon the Scotch Engagement, and lately refuſed to read your Declaration againſt Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> yet gave thanks when he was overcome; together with your haſty Vote for the continuance of Tythes, with other things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that might be mentioned, plainly declares you to be acted by the ſame ſpirit in owning carnall Intereſts in oppoſition to the Friends of the Cauſe as you were before.</note> 
               <hi>diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced the buſineſs of the poor People of God in</hi> Wales, <hi>who had watching over them men like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wolves, ready to catch the Lamb as ſoon as it was brought out into the world, that you ſignally threw that buſineſs under foot, to the diſcountenancing of the honeſt people there, and to the countenancing of the Malignant Party of this Commonwealth, which they ſay was as perfect a trial of your ſpirits as any thing, which many had felt by ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That they found you never intended good to the people of God, (to wit) that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of them under the ſeveral forms of godlineſs, and that your tenderneſs was forgotten to them all, though that by their hands and means it was (through the bleſſing of God) you then ſat where you did, and Affairs had been inſtrumentally brought to that iſſue they then were brought to, which was but an ill requital.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 34. 8. <hi>That though many words had been ſpoken to you for the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Law ſo much groaned under, in that poſture it then was in, yet many months together was not time enough to paſs over one word call'd incumberances, and this they ſay they found was your then ſpirit and complexion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>That they ſaw your intendment was to perpetuate your ſelves and men of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which ſome underſtood from your-own mouths, from your own deſigns, who could not endure to hear of being diſſolved, the which, had you been a Parliament never violated, ſitting as free and as clear as any ever ſat in</hi> Englaud, <hi>yet to go about to perpetuate your ſelves they thought was ſo great a breach of Truſt, as greater could not be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 35. <hi>That you did not proceed in wayes that were honeſt and ſafe to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in providing Qualifications of the Act of a New Repreſentative, ſo as to keep out Presbyters or Neuters, to put the power into whoſe hands they having deſerted the Cauſe and Intereſt upon the Kings account; and upon that cloſure between them and the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nation, was to have delivered up the Cauſe into the hands of Intereſſed and Byaſt men who had little affection to the Cauſe, and when the General and Officers made ſuch objections as to the danger of this proceeding that you could not but aſſent unto, yet anſwer was made as before, that nothing would ſave the Nation, but the continuance of your ſelves in Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 36. <hi>That you would not, though the Government was in that unſettled condition, and things being under ſo much ill ſenſe abroad, and ſo likely to come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in every reſpect if it went on ſo, anſwer the</hi> General and Officers <hi>deſire,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve the Truſt (then in your hands) over to perſons of honour and integrity, that were well known, men well affected to Religion, and the Intereſt of <hi>the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167283:6"/>Nation, which they told you, and had been confeſt by you, was no new thing when theſe Nations had been under the like burly burlies and diſtractions, which they offered to you out of the deep ſenſe they had of the good of theſe Nations and the Cauſe of Chriſt; which in all likelihood had been loſt, had the Power been longer continued in your hands. But the anſwer ſtill was, that nothing would ſave the Nation but the Continuance of that Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 36, 37. 12. <hi>That you dealt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">You dealt as cunningly and deceitfully with the Friends of the Cauſe in your ſecond Sitting, as formerly with the Army, for upon the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Petition, among others, againſt Tythes, you took the advantage one Morning, when ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral whom you thought would oppoſe you were abſent, and voted the continuance of them though (as it is reported) that buſineſs of Tythes was not to have been debated till about four dayes after; and thus did you carry it in putting Mr. <hi>Canne</hi> by from writing the Intelligence, and placing <hi>Ned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in his room; and how you likewiſe dealt treacherouſly with the Army a ſecond time, is very well known, which juggling trapanning practiſes of yours among other things, declares plainly you would have dealt as deceitfully in the buſineſs of the Repreſentative you were lately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, had you not been diſſolved a ſecond time. But I forbear to mention any further at preſent, though very much more might be ſpoken in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation that your ſpirit in your ſecond Sitting was worſe in every particular then in the time of your firſt.</note> 
               <hi>deceitfully with the General and the Officers of the Army in ſaying you would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſuſpend proceeedings with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative the next day till you had a further Conference with them, and yet for all this did you that very day proceed with all the eagerneſs you could, and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt finiſhed it, and brought it to that iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue with that haſte, that it had never been before, unſafely and diſhoneſtly leaving out the things that did neceſſarily relate to due Qualifications, and reſolved to make it a paper Bill not to ingroſs it, that ſo in a cheating manner you might make the quicker diſpatch of it, thus to have thrown away all the Liberties of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the hands that never bled for it; and therefore for the preſervation of the Cauſe (they ſay) they thought it their duty not to ſuffer it, and upon this the Houſe was diſſolved. Thus far is charged upon you in the forementioned Speech to the Little Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This we tell you</hi> [ſpeaking to the Little Parliament] <hi>that ſo you may know that what hath been done in diſſolving this Parliament, was as neceſſary as the preſervation of this Cauſe, and that neceſſity that led us to do that, hath brought us to this iſſue of exerciſing an extraordinary way and courſe to draw your ſelves together upon this account, that you are men who know the Lord, and have made obſervations of his marvellous diſpenſations, and may be truſted with the Cauſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words of the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> to the <hi>Little Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> thus laid before you, is given a perfect Character and Deſcription of the then (and may it not too truly be ſaid the late) frame of your Spirits, and what you would not do as to a more thorow carrying on his Work and Cauſe, as alſo what with all haſte you were doing againſt it; with ſeveral other things too truly laid to your Charge contained in this Speech: and that upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of theſe things you were diſſolved.</p>
            <p>Now what ever the deſign of the then <hi>General,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> and ſome other of his Machevilian politick Officers and Aſſiſtants was in diſſolving, and thus caſting durt upon you the Lord and themſelves beſt knows; who doubtleſs in his own time will (and hath begun to do already) diſcover, and bring all the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167283:6"/>hidden works of darkneſs, and ſecret wicked things to light; yet there then was (and as by after actions alſo did appear) very evident grounds to believe and ſay, it chiefly was to make way, and as a ſtirrup to get into the Power them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore, though it was unrighteouſly and wickedly done as to them, yet doubtleſs as juſt and righteous in the ſight of God, conſidering the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned evils laid to your charge, as was formerly the ſifting and purging your Houſe to hinder the perſonal Treaty and upon other accounts, or beheading the late King, and caſting out his Monarchy for his Tyranny; and diſſolving the laſt Parliament as enemies to, and oppoſers of the <hi>Cauſe of God</hi> and his people, that ſo your ſelves, or better then you, might come into their places, both of which according to mans Law, and the old almoſt ruined Conſtitutions of this Nation, are judged lawful <hi>Powers,</hi> as well as your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And although it be granted there was a deceitfull treacherous ſpirit which lay (like a ſerpent under the graſs) in the bottom of this action in ſome of the Army who pretended to be either the ſtone it ſelf mentioned, <note n="*" place="margin">See page 43 of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Book.</note> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. or at leaſt to have had ſomewhat of the ſpirit of it: So was there likewiſe at the ſame time an honeſt, ſingle, ſincere ſpirit among ſome of the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Navy,</hi> the <hi>Churches,</hi> and good people of the Nation, who were indeed for the work, and will ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long be found had then, and yet have the true ſpirit of the ſtone (in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) both planted, and abiding in them, who did very much approve of and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in your being diſſolved, and that upon the forementioned too true account given by the General and Officers of the Army, as is manifeſted in the latter end of the forementioned Speech to the Little Parliament (page 45. of that Book) in the following words.</p>
            <p>Sayes he, <hi>All that I have to ſay in my own, and in the names of my Fellow Officers, (who have joyned with me in this work) that we ſhall commend you to the Grace of God, and to the guidance of his Spirit having thus far ſerved you, or rather our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in it, we as we hope, and ſhall be ready in our ſtations, according as the Providence of God ſhall lead us, to be ſubſervient to the work of God, and the Authority which we reckon God hath ſet over us: And although we have no formal thing to preſent you with to which the hands and outward viſible expreſſions of the hearts of the Officers of the three Nations are ſet, yet we may ſay for them, and we may ſay alſo with confidence, that our Brethren at Sea, with whom neither in</hi> Scotland <hi>nor</hi> Ireland, <hi>nor at</hi> Sea, <hi>hath any Artifice been uſed to perſwade their approbation to this work, yet we can ſay, that their conſent and affections hath flowed into us beyond our expectations, and we may ſay with all confidence that we have had their approbation and full conſent ☞ unſought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to the other work,</hi> [to wit, in diſſolving of you] <hi>ſo that you have their hearts and affections in this, and not onely they, but we have very many papers from the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Whatever Churches, or other Perſons they were, that cloſed with former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, or thus freely ſent in their papers, or otherwiſe ſpake in approbation of your firſt Diſſolution, for not doing the good things promiſed: as alſo approved of the Call of the Little Parliament in order to the doing of them, and yet afterward cloſed with and abetted the Protectoral Government, which was raiſed up upon the ruines of the honeſt part of the Little Parliament, on purpoſe to hinder their doing thoſe good things, have turn'd their backs upon the Cauſe of Chriſt as well as the Army, and ought to repent of their great evil in ſo doing as well as they.</note> 
               <hi>Churches of God thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully both ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving what hath beene
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167283:7"/>done in removing obſtacles</hi> [that is in removing of you] <hi>and approving what we have done in this very thing,</hi> [to wit, in calling the Little Parliament.]</p>
            <p>In all which, together with the forementioned particulars of your Charge contain'd in that Speech and Letter, is ſet forth the matter of fact that was againſt you, together with the righteous judgement that for the ſaving of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> there was an abſolute neceſſity to paſs upon you, and alſo how moſt of the good people in the <hi>Army, Navy,</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> &amp;c. in the three Nations, did both approve of, and rejoyce therein.</p>
            <p>And to ſay the truth, there was but very few, compared with the others, who might then truly be ſaid were Friends to the Cauſe that were diſſatisfied; whoſe diſſatisfactions were not meerly becauſe you were diſſolved, and the other choſen in your ſtead, for they alſo complain'd of you, and deſired a <hi>New Repreſentative</hi> as well as others, but that it was done in ſuch a manner as in their then appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions not onely made way for the General to take the Power himſelf, but alſo tended to pluck up by the very roots the old way of chuſing Rulers, by the whole <hi>Bulk</hi> or <hi>Body</hi> of the people, which they called (and formerly was ſo) the <hi>Legall Foundations,</hi> which was then in their judgements (and ſtill is of ſome of them, who underſtand no better how to follow the Lord in his overturning diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) the onely legal and beſt way for the choice of Rulers. So that all things conſidered, ſetting aſide the forementioned diſſatisfactions of ſome, which was onely as to the manner, but not to the matter of your being diſſolved, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies little or nothing at all as to the clearing of you; it plainly appears, that for your unfaithfulneſs in, and unfitneſs for your ſtewardſhip, and not thoroughly improving the <hi>Talent</hi> which was then committed to you, for God and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, you were both by his Providence, and their Approbation and Conſent juſtly laid aſide. Inſomuch, that if the now true friends of the Cauſe, had either Light, and ſuitable thereunto, a <hi>ſincere, upright, courageous, ſingle,</hi> and <hi>lively Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as they ought to have, (and as the Saints ſhall have, when <hi>the Law ſhall go forth of Zion</hi>) to follow the Lord in his Overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpenſations, who as he hath formerly, and in our Day, ſo hath promiſed for the future ſafely to <hi>lead his People</hi> [on in his work] <hi>in wayes they have not gone with their feet,</hi> Iſa. 41.2. <hi>And to bring the blinde by a way they know not, and lead them in paths that they have not known, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 42.16. Would lay aſide the excrementitious outſide, ſhell, or notion of things relating to a further carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of the Cauſe in its purity; to wit, <hi>the ſpirit of the Nation,</hi> or <hi>whole body of the People,</hi> which the Lord by a continued ſeries of providential Diſpenſations (becauſe of the malignity of their ſpirits, againſt his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>People</hi>) hath one time after another caſt out, and witneſſed againſt; and on the other hand would look into the very <hi>ſpirit, kernel, and ſubſtance of things relating thereunto,</hi> to wit, <hi>the ſpirit of the good People who have gone on with the Lord in his work to this very day:</hi> who deſired, conſented, and approved of your being then laid aſide, you were really, clearly, deſervedly, and juſtly caſt out; and to ſay the truth, had not from that time to the very day of your ſecond Call, nor have not now, the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght to ſit again upon the former account, which I am perſwaded the Lord in due time will make manifeſt, notwithſtanding through the ſhort-ſightedneſs (though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167283:7"/>I truſt ſimplicity) of ſome friends who deſired (and were inſtrumental therein) you might be called to ſit a ſecond time, (and poſſibly by your ſelves) it is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended that there we went out of the way at firſt, and therefore muſt there begin again: But if I know any thing of the minde of God, (as I truſt through his Grace I do) by the obſervations that I have made of his footſteps in the carrying on of his work hitherto amongſt us, you are all miſtaken, and I know you will finde it ſo, which I doubt not but clearly to manifeſt in that which follows.</p>
            <p>For although we had many Deliverances and Victories, and the Lord emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently bleſt us with ſucceſs, and our dread was upon our Enemies both at home and abroad, whileſt you were ſitting, eſpecially towards the latter end, yet be it known unto you, it was not purely for your ſakes, conſidered as you were a <hi>Parliament</hi> in the Bulk, but as there was a ſincere, ſingle, honeſt ſpirit (according to their then light) acting for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> in ſome among <hi>You,</hi> in the <hi>Army,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Nation,</hi> which I conceive will be granted by every diſcerning perſon who was upon the place, and made obſervation of things; and which the late General <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and his then Officers, do alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in the forementioned Speech to the Little Parliament, Page 27. of that Book, in the following words.</p>
            <p>Sayes he, <hi>After divers turnings of Affairs, it pleaſed God much about the midſt of the War to winnow the Forces of this Nation, and to put them into the hands of men of other Principles, then thoſe that did engage at the firſt, &amp;c. Thoſe ſtrange windings and turnings of Providence, thoſe very great appearances of God in croſſing the deſigns of men,</hi> [to wit, <hi>Hollis, Stapleton,</hi> and the men of that ſpirit among you, and in the Army,] <hi>that he might raiſe up a contemptible company of men not verſt in Military Affairs, nor having much natural propencity to them, through the owning a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">If the General and Officers of the Army had kept cloſe to the practice of this honeſt Principle, thoſe Officers he hath left behinde him, and their pretended faithful brethren lately impriſoned in <hi>Scotland,</hi> had not been ſerved ſuch a <hi>Monckiſh</hi> treacherous trick as now they are; but they that deal treacherouſly with their Principles, as alſo ſtand by and aſſiſt whileſt their Brethren are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for their faithfulneſs thereunto, it is juſt with the Lord to ſuffer or appoint others to deal treacherouſly with them.</note> 
               <hi>Principle of Godlines, which ſo ſoon as it came to be owned, and the ſtate of Affairs put upon that foot of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how God bleſt them and all their undertakings, by the raiſing up of that moſt improbable, deſpicable, contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means, (for that we muſt for ever own) you very well known, &amp;c.</hi> He goes on.</p>
            <p>Page 27, 28. <hi>The iſſues of thoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes that God was pleaſed to give this Nation were very great things brought about, beſides the Dints that were upon thoſe Nations and places where they were carried on, even in the Civil Affairs, to the bringing Offenders to Juſtice, the ſtate of this Government to the Name at leaſt of a Commonwealth, the ſearching and ſifting of all Places and Perſons, the King removed and brought to Juſtice, and many great ones with him. The</hi> Houſe of Commons <hi>the</hi> Repreſentative <hi>of the People of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>winnowed, ſifted, and brought to a handful, &amp;c. All which great things</hi> were inſtrumentally brought forth by the honeſt Party, after the many ſtrivings and contendings with a Malignant, Rigid Presbyterian, Neutral, Corrupt Party among you, as the then General and Officers alſo confeſs in Page 28. of that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:167283:8"/>Book. Sayes he, <hi>As the effect of that memorable Year</hi> 1648. <hi>was to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bringing Delinquents to puniſhment, ſo it was of the Change of the Government, although it be true, if we had time to ſpeak, the carriages of ſome in Truſt, in moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Truſt, was ſuch as would have fruſtrated to us the hopes of all our undertakings, had not God miraculouſly prevented, I mean by that cloſure that would have beèn endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with the King, whereby we ſhould have put into his hand, all that Cauſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt we had oppoſed, and had nothing to have ſecured us but a little piece of paper, &amp;c.</hi> Which clearly confirms what I have ſaid, that the Lord bleſt us with ſucceſs in our <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Forces,</hi> as there was a ſincere ſpirit acting for the Cauſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Chriſt in that day and no otherwiſe, his free grace onely excepted.</p>
            <p>For when you were diſſolved, and the Little Parliament called, there was a greater preſence of God with them, a terrour upon the enemy <hi>both at home and abroad,</hi> eſpecially upon the <hi>Lawyers, National Clergy,</hi> and all other <hi>corrupt Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts;</hi> as alſo the hearts of moſt of the true friends to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> more rejoycing then in the time of your ſitting. But I let that paſs, and ſhall in the next place in ſome meaſure diſcover the myſtery of iniquity that lay in the bottom, and was working in Tranſactions after you were diſſolved, wherein lies the corrupt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or ſpring, (though unſeen by moſt people) from whence the late Apoſtacy had its riſe, which ſo cauſed the forementioned preſence of the Lord to depart from our Councills and Forces, and expoſed us to the reproach and ſcorn of our enemies both at home and abroad, and alſo occaſioned the late diſtractions, and diviſions, as between the true, ſo the true and falſe profeſſours amongſt us, and is as it were the pin and hinge, on which all the confuſion and dark apprehenſions of things have had their dependance and moving from that time to this very day, and is as follows.</p>
            <p>For after you were diſſolved, and the Little Parliament were about to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, beſides what was ſpoken to your ſelves, and was deſired of you by the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army;</hi> to wit, <hi>That you would divolve your truſt over to Perſons of Honour and Integrity, that were well known, men well affected to Religion, and the Intereſt of the Nation, &amp;c.</hi> He alſo declared in the preſence of Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cradock,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lockyer,</hi> and others who were in a private conſultation about that choice, <hi>That if there were one man more faithful to the Saints, and more ſuited to the work then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and that had not been left behinde in former diſpenſatious, by the bleſſing of God he ſhould be choſen, and that Relations, and all others not thus qualified, ſhould be reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and that from this Scripture, which was then mentioned by the party to whom theſe words were ſpoken, to wit, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11.12. <hi>Ephraim compaſſeth me about with lies, and the Houſe of Iſrael with deceit; but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithful with the Saints.</hi> The firſt part of which Scripture he and his Officers applied to you in the forementioned Speech to the Little Parliament, page 38. of that Book; <hi>viz.</hi> That like <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iſrael you had compaſſed God about with lies, and deceit, to wit, with your Faſtings and Thanksgivings, and other exerciſes</hi> [yet did not do the good you were call'd for] <hi>which they had all cauſe to lament of, but</hi> [the Little Parliament] <hi>were called by God to be faithfull with the Saints who were ſomewhat inſtrumentall in their Call, and to be juſt ruling in the fear of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:167283:8"/>Which principle was more publickly (though hypocritically) declared by them in that Speech page 41. of the forementioned Book, ſayes he to them, <hi>I confeſs I did never look to ſee ſuch a day as this, it may be nor you, when</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>ſhall be ſo</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">If Chriſt indeed be King of Nations as well as of Saints, as ſurely he is, and as the Officers of the Army have both here and elſewhere acknowledged him to be; and the Little Parliament was called to act upon his foundation, and to do all things in his Name upon an avowed account as their <hi>Judge, King,</hi> and <hi>Law-giver,</hi> as theſe their words import. And the Lord by his eminent preſence with, and refreſhing the ſpirits of ſuch as were faithful among them, as alſo rejoycing the hearts of his faithful people, and ſtriking a terror upon the enemy whileſt they were ſitting and endeavoured to be acting according to that bleſſed ſpirit and principle gave teſtimony thereunto; and the Spirit of the Lord, and his faithful people grieved, and his preſence, as alſo their prayers withdrawn, and the Nation almoſt ruined ſince they were rejected, and the Lord ſo wonderfully overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and blaſted the deſigns of whatever had enmity to, and was ſet up after it, and ſeems by thoſe his overturning diſpenſations not to be pleaſed till thoſe who have dealt thus treacherouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the real practice of this their declared principle, and to own that Spirit they have ſo rejected: Then whoſoever it is that ſhall be either laying, or building upon any other foundation, or be promoting any perſons into power on this ſide of it, though never ſo refined, do ſet down ſhort of what the Lord in that day had brought us unto, and are in the apoſtacy ſtill, and muſt be overturned as well as your ſelves and all others that have gone before them.</note> 
               <hi>own'd as he is this day, and in this world, Jeſus Chriſt is owned this day by you all, and you own him by your wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs in appearing here, and you manifeſt this (as far as poor creatures can) to be a day of the power of Christ by your willingneſs; I know you remember that Scripture,</hi> Pſal. 110.3. The people ſhall be willing in the day of thy power. <hi>God doth manifeſt it to be a day of the power of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having through ſo much Blood and Trials as have been upon theſe Nations made this to be one of the great Iſſues thereof to have a People called to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority upon ſuch an avowed account, God hath owned his Son by this, and you by your willingneſs do own</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c. <hi>I confeſs I did never look to ſee ſuch a ſight as this. We have not allowed our ſelves in the Choice of one perſon, of whom we had not this good hope, that there was faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and love to all the Saints; and thus God hath owned you, and by your comming together have you owned him, &amp;c.</hi> And towards the latter end of that Speech, [Book page 43.] he further ſaith unto them, <hi>Truly ſeeing things are ſo, that you are at the edge of the Promiſes and Propheſies, at leaſt if there were neither promiſe for this nor propheſie, you are to be coveting after the beſt things, endeavouring after the beſt things, and as I have ſaid elſewhere, If I were to chuſe the meaneſt Officer in the Army, or Commonwealth, I would chuſe a godly man that hath Principles, eſpecially where Truſt is to be committed, for I know where to have a man of Principles, I believe if any of you ſhould chuſe a ſervant you would do ſo, and I would all our Magiſtrates were ſo choſen, that may be ſome effects of this, it is our duty to chuſe men that fear the Lord, to praiſe the Lord, yea ſuch as the Lord forms for himſelf, and he expects not praiſes from others, &amp;c.</hi> In all which are good words ſpoken, and principles laid down, as if he and his Officers fully intended to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in the practice of them; but may not the true Friends of the Cauſe to the great grief and ſadneſs of their ſpirits, ſay of them, as the Lord concerning <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>They have well ſaid all that they have ſpoken, but oh that their hearts and tougues had gone together, that there had been indeed ſuch a heart in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:167283:9"/>them, as in ſincerity to have kept to the real practice of thoſe bleſſed principles, then had it been well with them, and with the poor Nation upon that account.</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe golden words and pretences, the Lord, my ſelf, and others knows, that there was at the ſame time, yea ſome time before theſe words were ſpoken, as in <hi>the ſeed of the ſerpent</hi> againſt <hi>the ſeed of the woman,</hi> or in the ſpirit of <hi>Saul</hi> and his followers againſt the ſpirit of <hi>David,</hi> and his followers, ſo a ſpirit of enmity and hatred ſecretly lodging in the breaſts of the then <hi>General,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Disbrow,</hi> Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering,</hi> Coll. <hi>Whaly,</hi> Coll. <hi>Goff, Dean Owen,</hi> (ſo called) and others, againſt ſeveral of thoſe honeſt men who were afterwards turned out of the Little Parliament, who were faithful Friends to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and indeed above others, and that upon Scripture grounds for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and moſt ſuited to thoſe good things, which the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> in the foregoing Speech do ſeem ſo much to preſs after, whoſe principles they ſeemingly moſt owned, and whoſe aſſiſtance they greatly deſired (pretending to be of one heart with them) in the diſſolving of you, and choice of the other, yet for no other cauſe then their preſſing, to be acting up to theſe principles in reality and power, was this enmity againſt them, which will afterwards appear ſo plainly, as he that runs may read it.</p>
            <p>For notwithſtanding the forementioned pretences and promiſes of chuſing none but what were <hi>faithful with the Saints,</hi> and <hi>moſt ſuited to the work,</hi> yet was there ſuch perſons who were of a contrary ſpirit and principle purpoſely choſen and packt together, (<hi>viz.</hi> Coll. <hi>Montague,</hi> Coll. <hi>Barton,</hi> Coll. <hi>Mathews,</hi> Sir <hi>William Roberts,</hi> Alderman <hi>Tichborn,</hi> and others) and thoſe the greater number, as that when the forementioned good things came to be done, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more refined oppreſſions which lay upon the good people and others to be taken away, they did ſo oppoſe and hinder the honeſt party in the Houſe, that very little or nothing at all could be done for them; the <hi>General,</hi> Ma. Gen. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> and the forementioned perſons ſecretly owning of, and holding a Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency with this corrupt Party all the while; which was ſuch unheard of <hi>juggling, deceit,</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> that when I moſt ſeriouſly and thorowly ſet my ſelf to conſider of it, I cannot but cry out with a holy deteſtation and abhorrency in my ſpirit, both of it and them, and ſay, Oh! the <hi>Hypocriſie, Treachery, Villany, Wickedneſs, and abominable unrighteouſneſs</hi> that lies hid in the bottom of the late and preſent Apoſtacy, and that ſurely the Lord who <hi>loveth righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>hates iniquity,</hi> and <hi>every falſe way,</hi> will not let ſo great, and not to be parallel'd wickedneſs paſs unpuniſht with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome more eminent publick repentance for the ſame, then hath yet been<note n="*" place="margin">If this wretched envious ſpirit did not yet remain, would they ſince your ſecond Diſſolution have been ſo forward to take into their New Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil <hi>Lawrence Strickland, Tichborn, Hewſon, Clark,</hi> and others of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt part of the Litttle Parliament, who left the Houſe and went to deliver up their pretended power to the General, upon which he was made Protector, and promoted and abetted the late Apoſtacy, and do what they can as it were to ſtave and keep off the faithful Friends of the Cauſe who are well known to be men of integrity, and well affected to the Intereſt of the Nation, which your not endeavouring to divolve the Truſt in your hands upon, was one of the great grounds why they pretendedly diſſolved you. The Lord who wil not be mocked, nor his faithful people whom both you and they have cheated and dealt unrighteouſly and hypocritically with all, will not long bear ſuch wicked actions at their hands.</note> manifeſted by them, and it will be well for them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:167283:9"/>if the aforeſaid enmity to the true ſpirit of their forementioned profeſt and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red principles, and to theſe very perſons and others like them who through grace in ſome meaſure are endued therewith, doth not yet remain untaken away, for herein (in a great meaſure) will lye the conteſt for the future, for either this hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical, ſelf-ſeeking, treacherous, envious ſpirit in the remaining Officers of the Army that have now power in their hands muſt be put away, and they really united to what they have ſo greatly profeſt and declared, and what they have ſo pretended to diſſolve you for nor doing of, which they have not been to this very day, or elſe there will be no peace from the Lord and his faithful people with them; and all their ſhrowding themſelves under your waſting, decaying wing, had you been ſitting, or under a power that is more refined then you, if ſhort of the ſpirit they have ſo rejected, and as it were crucified, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep down in the grave as the Souldiers did Chriſt in the dayes of his Humiliation, can ſave them <hi>from the wrath of God, and the Lamb, and his faithful followers.</hi> I ſhall now return to ſpeak a little further how and for what cauſe it was that the forementioned preſence of the Lord departed from, and went not forth to own and proſper the Councells and Forces of this Nation as before.</p>
            <p>As I ſaid before, when you were diſſolved, and the Little Parliament called upon the avowed account of the Son of God, and to be acting upon his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as he is King of Nations, and to do all things in his Name as their and our <hi>King, Judge,</hi> and <hi>Law-giver,</hi> Iſa. 33.22. as you may ſee by the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Speech they were called to do, and the perſons of the aforeſaid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſpirit and principle, who for ſome time (till the fiſh was caught and the bird taken) were ſeemingly owned, were labouring as it were in the very fire to bring forth in reallity what the <hi>General</hi> and his <hi>Officers</hi> ſo pretended to in words, and to own and preſerve the honeſt Intereſt, and taking away all the remaining<note n="*" place="margin">Among other Acts and Votes that paſt whilſt this honeſt Party fat, they prevailed for the paſſing of theſe four hereafter mentioned. Firſt, for abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and taking away the Court of Chancery, wherein was depending 23000. Cauſes, ſome of them having lain there five, ſome ten, ſome twenty, ſome thirty years and more, to the utter undoing of many Families. The ſecond Vote, for a New Body, or Moddel of the Law, then, and now ſo greatly deſired by good people, which your not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of was one other reaſon of your Diſſolution. A third Vote, the taking away the Power of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons to make Preſentations to Church Livings. The fourth was; that Innocent Negative Vote of not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the report of the Committee for Tythes, touching what they offered as the beſt way to eject ignorant, prophane, and ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, upon which preſently followed the Diſſolution of the Houſe. See a Book written by <hi>L. D.</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Mr Barhone</hi> then a member of that Houſe, ſold at the Crown in Popes head Alley, and worthy your taking notice of.</note> oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions lying upon the bodies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences both of them and others; not onely the ſame, but a greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and glory was with and upon our Councils and Forces, our ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour upon the Enemy both at home and abroad, and the hearts of moſt of the true Friends to the Cauſe of Chriſt, and the Commonwealth, more rejoycing then in the time of your firſt ſitting; yea, the very Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were angry, and began to be wondering and looking after the things that were coming upon them, as they ſhall more eminently be and do, when <hi>the Spirit of Life from God ſhall enter into the</hi> Lords faithful people, to revive that ſpirit, which in theſe perſons was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:167283:10"/>as it were trampled upon, caſt out, and crucified, according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11, 18. So alſo the Lawyers, Clergy, and all other corrupt Intereſts, to wit, the <hi>Adonijah,</hi> falſe ſpirit of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry in theſe Nations, were almoſt at their wits end, for fear their Corruption, Bribery, Dilatory proceedings in Law ſuits, Double Fees, Taking Fees from both parties, &amp;c. A Coercive power over their Brethren Conſciences, Tythes of all kinds, Power of haling their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners before Magiſtrates, Caſting them into Priſons, Seizing upon their Goods, and Forcing them to pay treble Dammages for non-payment of Tythes, and great Riches they gain'd upon this account would ceaſe, and be utterly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and were ready to faint, and cry out, as the more wicked Children of their dear Lady Mother, <hi>Myſtery, Babylon, the great Whore, and mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and abominations of the earth,</hi> both in the Magiſtracy, and Miniſtry thereof ſhall certainly, and more eminently do in the latter dayes, according to, <hi>Revel</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing no other way to help themſelves; By their Emiſſaries and Agents, (ſuch as <hi>Whitlock,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And it may too truly be ſuſpected that the ſame dark lanthorn ſpirit, and moſt of the ſame perſons are now at work with ſome of the Grandees of the Army, as in the time of your firſt Diſſolution, labouring as for life to keep ſuch faithful men from coming into power, as will ſuffer no cuſtom or practice, though never ſo ſpecious in the outward pretence, that is Oppreſſive, and without warrant in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to lie upon the Bodies or Conſciences of the Lords people. Which forementioned perſons and others of that ſpirit have been, and are the great Incendiaries, as was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>Strafford, Cottington, Canterbury, Wren,</hi> and others in their day: and I am very much out of the way if they leave not off, but perſiſt in this wicked underhand oppoſing the work of the Lord, that the wrath and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God and his people will break forth againſt them as againſt the former.</note> 
               <hi>St. Johns, Liſle,</hi> As alſo <hi>Philip Nye,</hi> (afterwards Metropolitane Tryer at <hi>White Hall</hi>) Deane <hi>Owen,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tho. Goodwin</hi> (ſo called) and others) they repair to the then <hi>General</hi> and ſome of his Officers, and to a Corrupt party in that <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> pack'd beforehand for ſuch a purpoſe, crying out as it were for help: which General, &amp;c. were as willing to receive and hearken to them as they to come; for that the aforeſaid honeſt Party in the Houſe did alſo ſtrike at their ſelf-ſeeking and corrupt Intereſts, and were labouring to bring the great Officers to ſerve the State (which was ſo impoveriſhed) a Year without pay, as alſo would render them very cheap, and have their perſons no further in admiration, then as they honoured the Lord, and their ſincerity to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> appeared. Wherefore the forementioned corrupt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being ſo well agreed, their <hi>Caſe</hi> alſo being alike deſperate, and knowing right well they could expect no better at their hands, being thus greatly afraid (as they are to this day) according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.6, 7. <hi>They helped every one his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,</hi> and each corrupt Intereſt <hi>ſaid to his Brother, Be of good courage.</hi> So the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Lawyer encouraged the <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> the Clergy-man the eminent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty man,</hi> the eminent Univerſity man the corrupt, ſelf-ſeeking <hi>General</hi> and his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> the General and his Officers (with the former) the corrupt Party in that <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> who upon a firſt day (Heathen-like called Sunday) on which they uſually pretend to worſhip God, and <hi>compaſs him about with lies,</hi> (an evill they ſo complained of in you) they held Cabals at <hi>Whitchall</hi> and the <hi>Cockpit</hi> to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:167283:10"/>conſult the Diſſolution of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> which being fully agreed and concluded upon, the Plot was ſo laid between them, that <hi>Sydenham, Montague, Pickering, Strickland, Lawrence, Clark,</hi> and others of the corrupt Party muſt get together betimes the next morning into the <hi>Houſe</hi> two hours, ſooner then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally without the honeſt Parties knowledge, and before they could get together and move a reſigning or tranſlating their pretended <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>General,</hi> that ſo his after <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> might appear with the greater face of <hi>Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and be accepted of by the good people; but as early as it was, this their wicked Motion met with oppoſition from the friends of the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> who came in unexpectedly upon them, inſomuch, that the <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> durſt not hazard to put the forementioned Motion to the Vote; but without either <hi>Vote</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journment</hi> to any other place or time, they with their <hi>Speaker</hi> in all haſte go away to <hi>White-Hall</hi> to deliver up their pretended <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>General,</hi> leaving a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of the <hi>honeſt Party</hi> behinde them in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> who in a little time after were by that <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Traytor</hi> both to God and Man, Coll. <hi>Goff,</hi> and Lieu. Collonel <hi>White</hi> (ſince drowned coming from <hi>Mardike</hi>) and Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers they brought (who are alwayes ready for any villany they are put upon) turn'd out of the <hi>Houſe;</hi> thereby thinking and endeavouring ſo <hi>to faſten</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of their corrupt Intereſts, and therewith all the remaining oppreſſions lying both upon the Bodies and Conſciences of the Lords People <hi>with nails, that it ſhould not be moved,</hi> and thus the buſineſs ſtands between the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and that <hi>honeſt Party</hi> of that <hi>Little Parliament</hi> to this very day.</p>
            <p>In doing which wicked action, and therein diſcountenancing, perſecuting, yea what in them lay as it were crucifying this honeſt Spirit in theſe perſons, who were bringing forth the forementioned good things, which the <hi>Army</hi> ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſed, declared, and pretended to fight for, and which you were diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for not doing of. And the <hi>General</hi> thus ſetting up himſelf upon the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical,</hi> or <hi>Beaſt-like Foundation,</hi> ſo contrary to former Declarations, and as it were upon the ruines of the very ſpirit and principles, which he and his Officers but a little before had ſo greatly pretended to own, and be of themſelves, and alſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very ſame, yea worſe things then for which the late King was beheaded, and which they alſo condemned in you; as alſo <hi>Perſecuting, Impriſoning,</hi> and <hi>Baniſhing</hi> ſome of the forementioned faithful Friends of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> and others of the Lords people, and blaſpheming the Spirit of the Lord in them, ſaying, <hi>They were acted by a giddy headed, raſh, fanatick, devilliſh Spirit;</hi> and this for no other cauſe, then their faithfulneſs to the Lord, in preſſing after the good things according to their forementioned declared Principles, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the <hi>General</hi> and his <hi>Officers</hi> backſliding from them, and doing things, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically contrary thereunto, therein falſifying their <hi>Truſt,</hi> and <hi>building again what they</hi> formerly <hi>had deſtroyed,</hi> and declared againſt; the <hi>Army</hi> and all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned corrupt Intereſts, with ſeveral Independent, and<note n="*" place="margin">The good things they deſired in thoſe Addreſſes doth no more excuſe their evil in addreſſing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by abetting that Tyrannical Beaſt-like Government, then the Devils bringing Scripture in his mouth excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his wickedneſs in tempting of Chriſt.</note> ſome Baptized Churches, by their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Addreſſes, and otherwayes in the mean while countenancing,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:167283:11"/>encouraging, abetting, and upholding them therein, by all which the bleſſed Cauſe and work of Chriſt was very greatly ſtopt and hindered, the Spirit of the Lord and his People grieved.</p>
            <p>Now ſince theſe with many other wicked things that might be mentioned came to be done by that profeſſing hypocritical generation, the forementioned glorious preſence that was formerly with you, the Little Parliament, and their Councils and Forces was withdrawn, the courage of the enemy heightned, the corrupt Intereſts before mentioned lifting up their heads and rejoycing, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.10. The Nations abroad contemn and ſcorn us; the lively freſh ſpirit for the work and Cauſe of Chriſt, which ſeem'd formerly to be in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my very much choaked and loſt; the hearts and prayers of the remaining faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friends of the Cauſe which were formerly with and for them, now grieved, and engaged againſt them, by all which the ſtate and condition of this poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, and is very greatly impaired, our Land Forces waſted and conſumed at <hi>Hiſpaniola, Jamaica, Mardike, Flanders,</hi> and elſewhere, our Shipping leſſened and diminiſhed; our Stores and Proviſions for Sea and Land expended and very much conſumed, and but very very little or no profit; our Magazines emptied, Treaſures waſted, Trade in a very great meaſure loſt and decayed, as Tradeſmen of all ſorts, and Shopkeepers (many of whom are broken, and are breaking eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day) finde by ſuch ſad and woful experience, as they never did before, nor in the memory of man was the lke ever known or heard of, (though Mr. <hi>Nye, Tho: Goodwin, Dean Owen,</hi> (ſo called) and the Officers and Meſſengers of above one hundred Congregations in <hi>England</hi> could tell their late <hi>Protector,</hi> that they and the Nation had <hi>not eaten the Bread of Adverſity, nor drunk the Water of Affliction, but had ſerved God in the abundance of all things;</hi>) Very great new debts contracted, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of old being ſatisfied, all which ſad effects, with others that might be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, (as was ſaid before) he that hath but half an eye, or that runs may read, is the bitter fruit of the Apoſtacy, Treachery, and Crucifying the Spirit of the Lord in the Members turned out of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> who were bringing forth that <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which the <hi>Army</hi> and good People of the three Nations were ſo greatly engaged in, and was no other then what the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Friends of the Cauſe are calling for in this day, and will give the Lord nor them no reſt till they do obtain.</p>
            <p>All things going thus contrary to the ſinful deſires and vain expectations of the upholders, and abbettors of this great Apoſtacy, (notwithſtanding the many helps they had to carry it on;) yet as if they had been left by the Lord to ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and procure their further deſtruction, they not onely afreſh impriſon the Lords faithful people for witneſſing againſt them, but alſo ſuffer others of them to be haled before Magiſtrates, caſt into priſons, forced to pay trebble damma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their goods to be ſeized upon, and ten times more taken away then their pretended due came to, for not paying of Tythes, and this greatly approved of by the then General (his Officers and all his worthy Addreſſors upholding him therein,) who was once the head of the Sectaries, out of a carnal deſign to draw in the Presbyterian Cleargy to ſtand by his Intereſt; who ſince the New Moddel, and beheading the late King, to this very day, it is well known have been ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:167283:11"/>to, and oppoſers of the Lords <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Cauſe,</hi> that hath been, and is yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be carryed on in theſe Nations. Though he and his Officers not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had as good as acknowledged in the forementioned Speech to the Little Parliament. See Book, page 40. 41. that the now Miniſtry of <hi>England,</hi> as to their then, and preſent ſtanding derived it ſelf, and ſucceſſion through the Papacy, and therefore a falſe ſucceſſion, and none to be the true ſucceſſion but what was <hi>through the Spirit given in that meaſure the Spirit is given, which</hi> [ſayes he] <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are well able to diſcerne and do.</hi> And yet for all this, contrary to Scripture or Reaſon, forced them to pay ſuch Miniſters as they judged were not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of a work of Grace in their hearts, much leſs of the Spirit for that work, but alſo derived their ſucceſſion through the Papacy, wherein with other things of this nature that might be mentioned; it appeared their tenderneſs was forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Lords people under ſeveral forms as much as yours, and that the cauſe of the people of God was deſpiſed by them.</p>
            <p>Thus were things going on, one the one hand, and ſome of the Lords faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people, called <hi>Sectaries, Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Fifth Monarchy men</hi> by their Faith, Prayers, Appeals, Propheſyings, and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt the Apoſtacy, and Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of it, counterworking and pulling down on the other, which honeſt, faithful ſpirit in them to the Lord, his Cauſe, and intereſt, can, will never leave working nor overturning till our Lord Jeſus Chriſt comes whoſe right it is. This rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of witneſſing Sectaries (ſo called) get ground, all the deſigns and ſtratagems made uſe of to quell them, and to uphold and ſtrengthen the Protectoral Beaſt-like foundation in himſelf and family were fruſtrated, and came to nothing; the Lords faithful people rejoyce, the old Protector (ſo called) is greatly troubled, grows faint, his heart as it were falls flat, and he dyes. I do the rather mention theſe things that you may the better remember the ſeveral ſteps of providence preceding your ſecond coming into power.</p>
            <p>The <hi>light, the delight of their eyes, the breath of their Noſtrils,</hi> their <hi>Moſes, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, great Mordecay,</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> or rather the moſt Famous Renowned Prince of their Apoſtate Congregation, who was gotten ſo far on of his journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Zion;</hi> yet by himſelf, and them through unbelief, and a ſelf-ſeeking, ſelf-exalting ſpirit, made their great Captain to return back again into <hi>Babylon,</hi> being thus taken away, and therein, their head, as it were, ſtruck from of their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; the remaining body of the Apoſtates, to wit, the late <hi>Council, Army, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Cleargy, Tryers, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity men, &amp;c.</hi> either not ſeeing, or rather being aſhamed it ſhould be known they ſaw this their ſin of Apoſtacy from the Cauſe of Chriſt, and how the preſence of the Lord was departed from them upon that account; inſtead of acknowledging the ſame and returning into the way from whence they had ſo treacherouſly and wickedly departed, and was the cauſe of all this evil that was upon them and the Nation, they go on like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blinde Bayards, or as a people beſotted in their former evil wayes, and to mend the matter, or lick themſelves whole again, they ſet up <hi>Richard Cromwel</hi> the eldeſt ſon of that family, upon his deceaſed Fathers Throne, thereby endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what in them lay, to confirm and eſtabliſh the aforeſaid Tyrannycal, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Power which they had exerciſed in the life time of his Father, who to eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:167283:12"/>himſelf more ſtrongly therein he calls a Parliament, choſen by the whole bulk or ſpirit of the Nation, as did his father before him, without any reſpect had to thoſe good qualifications, which you not being ſo honeſt to provide for in the Act of a New Repreſentative you were about, in the time of your former ſitting, was charged upon you as one of the great crimes, that it ſeems would have been committed by you, for which they pretended you were diſſolved.</p>
            <p>Theſe perſons ſo choſen come together, ſome of whom were friends to a Commonwealth Government in oppoſition to that of a Single perſon, yet moſt of theſe (as was in his Fathers Parliaments) very ſhort of that<note n="*" place="margin">Your unwillingneſs to divolve your truſt over to perſons of Honour, and Integrity, who were well affected to Religion and the Intereſt of the Nation for the further carrying on of the Cauſe of Chriſt, was another of the pretended Reaſons why the Army firſt diſſolved you; and yet afterward, as here may be ſeen, they did worſe themſelves.</note> excellent lively ſpirit for Government, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of Righteouſneſs, which the diſpenſation that is upon us calls for from Rulers in this our day, and theſe three Nations; ſo that no great good could be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from them had they not been overvoted by the greater pary that were of a contrary ſpirit to them.</p>
            <p>The other part of the Houſe which were very much the greater number conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of perſons tainted with both the Old and New Court Intereſt, who like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> brethren in iniquity, would alwayes be ſure to joyn together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commonwealths men, and others, to hinder whatever tended to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that intereſt or way of Government, and did ſtrike at the dethroning of their own, and of theſe the Old<note n="*" place="margin">Your not endeavouring in the time of your firſt ſitting to keep out Presbyters, Neuters, and Maſignants from coming into Power, was another of the pretended Reaſons why the Army diſſolved you; yet therein alſo as may be ſeen they did the ſame themſelves. I mention theſe things not to excuſe you, or in the leaſt to make diviſions, but that the poor people of God and the Nation may the better ſee and know how likely they are to be ruined and undone between the Army and you. Oh that ever men, who have profeſt to be the Army of the Lamb, and ſuch profeſſing men as many of you would be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon to be, ſhould ever deal ſo treacherouſly with the Cauſe of God, and his people, as you have done!</note> Malignant, Neutral and Presbyterian ſpirit were predominant, who endeavoured (covertly) all they could to bring things to run in the old Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Channel, and to be laying bonds upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as well as upon the bodies of the Lords people, called Sectaries; as alſo if they had been ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go on would have disbanded, if not the whole Army, yet at leaſt have purged out all therein, whom they had judged to have been ſuch factious ſeditious perſons; as Sir <hi>Arthur Haſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> (who then pretended to be a more faithful friend to the honeſt frinds of the Cauſe, then in this time of your ſecond ſitting he hath proved to be) and others, very well know.</p>
            <p>Things going on in this manner, and the <hi>Braſs, Iron,</hi> and <hi>Clay</hi> of this <hi>Toe</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Horne</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> mixing and agreeing no better together, and the pretended honeſt part of the Army ſo likely to be caſt out, and as it were undone if things went on ſo; they conſult together, and conclude, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would preſerve themſelves, and the honeſt Intereſt but the diſſolution of that Parliament; in order to which, they rendezvouz together in their arms the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:167283:12"/>night before, in ſeveral places of the City and about <hi>White-hall. Richard Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> the then Protector, Coll. <hi>Goff.</hi> Com. Gen. <hi>Whaly</hi> and others of the Army who cloſed with this corrupt party of that Parliament, at the ſame time endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring all they could to draw away a party or all engaged with the other to ſtand by them, fearing that their Kingdom would alſo be ſtruck at or diminiſhed by this buſineſs, the pretended honeſt part of the Army prevail and ſend to the aforeſaid <hi>Richard Cromwell,</hi> (a pretended legal Authority) deſiring him by his power to diſſolve that Parliament (who ſore againſt his will) anſwered their deſire therein, whereby they apprehended they were Legally Diſſolved.</p>
            <p>This great overturning diſpenſation being thus brought about, the Lords faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people and all others that may truly be ſaid were friends of the Cauſe, did greatly concurr with, and approve of what was done by the Army, in procuring the Diſſolution of that wretched Parliament, and did bleſs the Lord for the ſame, and likewiſe deſired, and greatly preſſed after the Diſſolution of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectoral Government</hi> alſo, as that which they formerly in the King, and now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſo lately in the <hi>Protector</hi> (ſo called) had the too ſad experience was Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical and Oppreſſive, and altogether inconſiſtent with the well being of the people of theſe Nations, and were not without ſome hopes. The Army having but a little before Declared to the world, <hi>They could not but bewail their great failings and turnings aſide, and wherein ſoever they had back-ſlidden they deſired to take ſhame to themſelves, and that they were now as ever equally endeared to the good Old, Cauſe and utter enemies to all Tyranny and Oppreſſion, &amp;c.</hi> but that they would have gone on to endeavour with all their might to have brought things to that perfection and ſtate they were in when the forementioned preſence and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord, was with, and upon us, to wit either to the choyce of the ſame, or other perſons of that honeſt ſpirit, and principle who were formerly turned out of the Little Parliament, (who have not ſince defiled their Garments with the late Apoſtacy, or if they have, have repented publickly for the ſame) the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from, and rejecting of which ſpirit and principle, by the then, and now buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, was the onely chief Cauſe of the Lords, ſo withdrawing his preſence from their <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Forces</hi> ſince that time.</p>
            <p>In order to which ſeveral faithful friends to the Cauſe in diſcharge of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and duty (as they then apprehended) to ſerve the Lord in that preſent juncture of affairs, did draw up, and (by the hands of Major <hi>Mallery,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Pinchin,</hi> Captain <hi>Cuſt,</hi> and others) preſent to Lieutenant General <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and the <hi>General Council of Officers</hi> a paper, called the <hi>Good Old Cauſe, Stated,</hi> which holds forth that the Army themſelves did formerly declare for and approve of that very ſpirit, and principle, and ſuch perſons to be in Power, as is before mentioned and therein was deſired.</p>
            <p>Now whether it was that the ſpirit of the Army which was ſo deeply drench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as it were over head and ears in the late Apoſtacy, like <hi>old Bottles,</hi> could not bear the <hi>new wine,</hi> to wit, the ſelf-denying ſpirit in the forementioned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons turned out of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> and in others like them, that was the reaſon they were not called again, or what the matter was; but to be ſure if they and the people who called you had been right and clear in their underſtandings,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:167283:13"/>or had had a true hint or taſte upon their ſpirits of that Bleſſed, Excellent, Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit that ſhall execute the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs that ſhall be when <hi>the Law ſhall go forth of Zion,</hi> and our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Saints ſhall <hi>reign in Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 32.1. They would have walked in that matter leſs by ſence, and more by faith, have truſted God, and never called you. But ſo it came to paſs, that through the darkneſs and ſhort-ſightedneſs of ſome of the Friends of the Cauſe and according to their deſires you were called together again to take your former Power, as being in the outward appearance <hi>the onely viſible Legall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Nation, The beſt expedient to root out the Monarchicall Protectorall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; To raiſe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Indeed you were very good at raiſing money and Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſecure your ſelves, and at going to Feaſts prepared out of the Orphans money by the carnal vain Magiſtrates of the City, to bribe and blinde you, that you might not ſearch into and purge out the fooliſh, apiſh, corrupt practices, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive Cuſtoms that are amongſt them, and from framing the Government of the City in the way of a Commonwealth, as you had declared the Government of the Nation to be. And at voting the continuance of Tythes, and therewith your wicked Ordinance for trebble dammages; at raiſing Enemies to the Cauſe under Collonel <hi>Thomſon,</hi> to ballance and put a check upon the faithfull Friends thereof; at perpetuating your ſelves as before, by filling up your Houſe with new Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; at owning corrupt Intereſts, and preferring corrupt perſons into places of Truſt, contrary to your own Votes and Declarations; at diſcountenancing the buſineſs of the friends of the Cauſe, to the countenance of the enemies thereof; at dealing deceitfully with the Army and Friends of the Cauſe; as backward to reform the Law, as alſo to divolve the Truſt lately in your hand over into the hands of faithful men, as formerly you were, and as ready to do the ſame, yea worſe things then in the ſeverall foregoing Particulars is charged againſt you: But as for the Cauſe of Chriſt accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true intent and ſpirit of it, the Juſt, Civil, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Liberties of the good People, and providing Perſons of a more excellent ſpirit for Government, to promote and bring this forth you underſtood it not, nor laid it to heart no more then the Army, and therefore very unmeet to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, but diſſolved as formerly.</note> 
               <hi>Money, And to prevent future War and Bloudſhed, Maintain the Good Old Cauſe, the Liberties and Freedoms of the good people in the things of God relating to the Conſcience, until ſuch time as a better Moddel of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be found out;</hi> ſo that here was your then Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>call</hi> and <hi>Standing,</hi> by all which it is probable you might apprehend the Lord did own you, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you retained the ſame ſpirit as before; and that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of your more then ſix years diſmiſſion from your former Power, had onely been putting you (as formerly <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon</hi>) <hi>to eat graſs with the Beaſts of the Field,</hi> Dan. 4.25. or made you as ordinary men, that ſo you might the better underſtand and know, <hi>that the moſt High ruled in the Kingdoms of men, and gave them to whomſoever he would,</hi> thereby to humble and make you better.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing you were once more brought together into the <hi>Power,</hi> not called thither by Malignants, Presbyterians, or the late new Court Party, who profeſs to remain in that ſpirit, but by ſome of the faithfull Friends of the Cauſe, and the Army, who as they ſay (though honeſt men think otherwiſe) are returned from their Apoſtacy, to do the forementioned good things till ſuch time onely as a better Moddel was found out, who in caſe you anſwer'd not what you were call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, had alſo the ſame power to take from you again what they had ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you; you ſhould not have been high minded, but feared, and been
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:167283:13"/>looking about you, and conſidering whether the ſame or a worſe ſpirit had not been in you now then formerly, and have taken heed of doing the ſame or worſe things that ſo cauſed the Friends of the Cauſe and the Army to complain of you, and ſo greatly deſire your Diſſolution, and a New Repreſentative to come in your places. For if during the time of your almoſt ſeven years Diſmiſſion from your former Power, you had only been like unto <hi>Nebuchadnezars ſtump,</hi> Dan. 4.15. root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the earth, and <hi>bound</hi> as it were <hi>about with iron and braſs,</hi> and had not repented and broken off your former ſins and evils charged upon you by the Army and others, and grown better by the ſhame and affliction of being ſo laid aſide, but ſtill remained as at your firſt Diſſolution, you could not honeſtly expect that the Friends of the Cauſe who called you onely to do thoſe good things which the Army pretendedly diſſolved you for not doing of, would take it well at your hands, or bear you herein, becauſe the former glory and preſence of the Lord that was with the Councels and Forces of this Nation, is by reaſon of the late and preſent Apoſtacy almoſt clean departed, and we as it were upon our laſt legs, and do well underſtand (ſome of them at leaſt who are more clear-ſighted) that it is not barely the name of a Commonwealth Government, and a people of a low, dull ſpirit and underſtanding exerciſed therein, who like ſo many heavy liſtleſs horſes put into their gears, muſt either draw or be whipt to it, as moſt of you were in the time of your firſt Sitting, and to the day of your late diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. But the Righteouſneſs and Juſtice thereof executed and brought forth with an excellent, lively, freſh ſpirit, by an humble, gracious, willing people, who have the concernments and wellfare of the Nation upon their hearts more then their own, and are tender unto, and faithful with all the Saints, anointed thereunto by the Lords Spirit, (which once the Army ſo greatly pretended to own) that will ſave and exalt theſe ſinking Nations, and do ſee that thither we muſt come, or we periſh, and therefore if you would not ſpeedily put to your helping hand in this criſis of danger, to bring this in, but would from time to time, as in the time of your firſt Sitting either continue your ſelves with your old ſpirit, or not before your riſing ſo provide as to keep out <hi>Cavaleers, Neuters, Presbyters,</hi> and the late <hi>New Court Party</hi> from coming into Power for the future (as there was very little likelihood you would, ſo many among you having Apoſtatized from your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Acts, Votes, and Declarations, and fell in with the Protectorall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nay voted for Kingſhip again, and therein dealt treacherouſly with the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt, and your own Principles, as well as the Army) you could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any other from them and the Army, if their hearts were ſincere and upright with God indeed, as they lately pretended to be, but that they would take care to do it themſelves, though as formerly a deſperate diſeaſe had a deſperate cure.</p>
            <p>And it ſeems for this very cauſe among others, it was that you were ſo lately diſſolved a ſecond time, whereby it very plainly appears that your late call to the Power was not a diſpenſation from the Lord to manifeſt we went out of the way in your firſt diſſolution, but onely that the neceſſity and juſtneſs thereof might more plainly appear not onely to your ſelves, but to the ſatisfaction of ſome friends of the Cauſe, that could not otherwiſe be ſatisfied but by the late tryal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:167283:14"/>of your ſpirits a ſecond time. As alſo that you might be inſtrumental (as the righteous judgement of the Lord upon them) to take away the Power, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Splendor, and Greatneſs of that family, which was ſo hypocritically, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly, and wickedly raiſed up upon your, and the honeſt part of the little Parliaments ruines though in the outward pretence, and ſhew for better ends, and this your work being done, to be removed again as before, that ſo a ſecond trial might be upon the ſpirits of the Army to ſee whether according to their former and late pretences, they would indeed be ſo honeſt (having ſo greatly miſt it hitherto,<note n="*" place="margin">The Lord hath one time after another ſince the Army rejected their profeſt ſpirit and principles, in caſting out the honeſt part of the Little Parliament, (as upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of old, who would not let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go to <hi>Canaan, Exod.</hi> Chap. 7. to Chap. 12.) ſo blaſted their deſigns, and thereby plagued and brought them down, as they are neceſſitated for their own preſervation to ſend unto and call upon the faithful Remnant (as did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi>) to pray for, adviſe with, and come into their aſſiſtance, as if he would force them to let them go; and doubtleſs will never let them reſt till they acknowledge their iniquity, and return to walk with more refinedneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their former honeſt Principles.</note> and thereby <hi>Pharaoh</hi>-like hindered the Lords faithfull people from going to <hi>Zion</hi>) as to bring in better and more ſuitable perſons then your ſelves (whom they had ſo greatly complained of) into the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation, to carry on with life and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the bleſſed <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> of the Lord for the future, which both you and they notwithſtanding your many high profeſſions have ſo greatly oppoſed and dealt treacherouſly withal.</p>
            <p>I might have been more large in comparing your ſpirit and actions in your late ſecond Sitting with the forementioned Particulars charged upon you by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army as the grounds and reaſons of your firſt Diſſolution, and have ſhewn more fully wherein you were rather worſe then in the time of your firſt Sitting; but it being more properly the Armies work to do it for their further vindication, who have in the Generall done ſomething therein already in their Plea they ſet forth for your late Diſſolution, I ſhall leave it to them, or to ſome other perſons who were more upon the place, and could better obſerve you then my ſelf, (who had little heart to come where you were upon the forementioned account) and ſhall conclude with (I hope) a <hi>Seaſonable Word</hi> by way of <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Propoſal</hi> to the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> themſelves, of whom the true Friends of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> have to this day too great reaſon to ſay, having had ſuch ſad and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience of their Adulteries from their former honeſt principles, neighings, and going a whoring after the <hi>accurſed thing,</hi> to wit, the Monarchical Tyrannical Power, Pomp, and Greatneſs, and their great lewdneſs and abominations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in committed, yea greater then for which the late King was beheaded, and they alſo pretended to diſſolve you a firſt and ſecond time, and yet like the Whore, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.20. wipe their mouths as if they had done no wckiedneſs. <hi>But are now as ever equally endeared to the</hi> Good Old Cauſe, <hi>and utter enemies to all Tyranny and Oppreſſion,</hi> when as the Lord and his people, yea the carnal people of the Nation, knows it is not ſo: As the Lord concerning <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of old, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.27. <hi>O Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Army, will you not be honeſt, ſincere, upright, deny your ſelf-Intereſt and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:167283:14"/>and he in reality what you have ſo greatly profeſt! Will you not return from whence you are fallen, and ſo truly be ſaid to repent, muſt you needs ruine the Nation by your continuing to go on in your Apoſtacy and Wickedneſs,</hi> will you not be clean, when ſhall it once be?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A Seaſonable Word by way of Counſel and Propoſal to the Officers of the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu may by reading over the foregoing <hi>Word</hi> to the <hi>Remaining Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> lately ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whom you have now diſſolved a ſecond time (as it concerns you ſo to do) take notice of almoſt all the moſt conſiderable circumſtances relating to the Bleſſed Cauſe and Work of Chriſt, that you and the good people of this Nation have been ſo long engaged in; and upon what account it was that the Lord ſo greatly bleſt the <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Forces</hi> of this Nation againſt the common enemy, whileſt it was carrying on; alſo how the forementioned good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſired that the <hi>Righteouſneſs, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>good things</hi> promiſed both by you and them, might be brought forth, and the Remaining more refined Oppreſſions lying upon their <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Conſciences</hi> taken away, as an improvement of all thoſe great Mercies and Victories which the Lord had ſo wonderfully and graciouſly beſtowed upon us: And how they likewiſe deſired that the then Long Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> being ſhort of ſpirit for the further carrying on of this work (as they were to the very day of their ſecond Diſſolution) might be diſſolved, and that other more ſuitable perſons thereunto then they were, might be called to do it; as alſo how greatly you ſeem'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur and go along with them therein, as being of one heart with them, declaring that you would have none to come into the Power for the future, but <hi>Perſons of Honour and Integrity, that were well known, men well affected to Religion, and the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Nation; Men who knew the Lord, and had made obſervations of his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous diſpenſations; Juſt men, ruling in the fear of God; A willing people, who had faith in Jeſus Chriſt, love to, and were faithful with all the Saints,</hi> men who were called <hi>choſen, and faithful,</hi> yea that <hi>it was your duty to chuſe men that feared the Lord to praiſe the Lord, ſuch as he had formed for himſelf, becauſe he expected not praiſes from others;</hi> as alſo pretended you diſſolved the Old Parliament for their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs and backwardneſs in bringing forth theſe things; yet how hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, treacherouſly, and unrighteouſly your ſelves afterwards dealt, and went directly contrary thereunto in rejecting the good you had ſo greatly pretended to thirſt after the accompliſhment of, and doing the very ſame, yea worſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:167283:15"/>things then you had ſo complained againſt them for, your after actions compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſeveral Particulars of your Charge againſt the aforeſaid Old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken out of your forementioned Letter to Lieu. Gen. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> then in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the then <hi>Generals Speech</hi> in his own and your names to the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Little Parliament</hi> before their Sitting, do very plainly manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Did the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> mannage their Affairs evilly in the time of their firſt Sitting, and did as evilly in rejecting the Councel and Advice you gave them, and the means you uſed to have had them done the good things promiſed both by you and them, and was of due to be performed tending to the Settlement of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> in Peace and Righteouſneſs? So did you. For after their firſt Diſſolution you rejected the wholeſome councel given you by your faithfull friends, as to the choice of perſons that would indeed bring forth that good you ſo greatly pretended to be thirſting after, and dealt deceitfully and treacherouſly with your then declared ſpirit and principle, as to the Qualifications of Rulers for ſo good a work, packing that <hi>Little Parliament</hi> for the moſt part with ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted perſons, ſuch as Alderman <hi>Tichborn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> Coll. <hi>Montague,</hi> Mr. <hi>Strickland,</hi> Sir <hi>William Roberts,</hi> Coll. <hi>Barton,</hi> the late Coll. <hi>Mathews,</hi> Collonel <hi>Clark,</hi> and others, who were contrary to that honeſt publick ſpirit and principle, which but a little before you had ſo greatly pretended to own in the Diſſolution of the <hi>Old</hi> and choice of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> who whileſt they were ſitting hindered the <hi>Honeſt Party</hi> among them (as you have heard before) from doing thoſe good things that would indeed have ſettled the Commonwealth in Peace and Righteouſneſs, and you their encouragers, and confederates all the while.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Did the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> do evilly in endeavouring all they could to perpetuate themſelves, and thereby all the Oppreſſions that then were upon the people, by filling up their Houſe with men of the ſame corupt Spirit and Principles with themſelves in order thereunto? As alſo in not laying the Government up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhoulders of ſuch men as would hopefully give the people the fruit of all their labour and blood and encourage good men for the future to venture their lives againſt the common enemy? So did you. For you very well know that the buſineſs was ſo laid between you and the forementioned <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> of that <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> as that they not onely hindered the <hi>Honeſt Party</hi> among them from the doing of that good whileſt they ſat, and providing for the ſure lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Government</hi> upon the ſhoulders of faithful men for the future, but that they might for ever hinder them from ſo doing, and thereby uphold both your own and their ſeveral ſelf Intereſts, and all the remaining Oppreſſions that then were, and to this very day are lying upon the people; in a clandeſtine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret manner without the honeſt Parties knowledge or conſent, wherein you dealt deceitfully and treacherouſly with them, (the like carriage in the <hi>Old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> to you a firſt and ſecond time, was another pretended reaſon of their firſt and ſecond Diſſolution) you conſult together, and ſo order the matter, that the aforeſaid <hi>Corrupt Party,</hi> with the <hi>Speaker,</hi> muſt leave the Houſe, and bring away their <hi>Power</hi> to your <hi>Geverall,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Goff,</hi> &amp;c. preſently be ſent with ſouldiers to turn out the other, and your <hi>General</hi> ſoon after be ſet up upon the <hi>Monarchical, Protectoral, Beaſt-like</hi> Foundation, with a <hi>Negative Voice</hi> in all things
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:167283:15"/>that oppoſed his Government, as alſo the <hi>Power of the Militia,</hi> during his life, and afterwards to his Succeſſor, which the Lord, his people, and your ſelves had ſo greatly witneſſed and declared againſt, and which coſt ſo much Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to oppoſe in the <hi>King,</hi> end eavouring all you could to uphold and perpetuate him and your ſelves therein, with all the Pride, Pomp, Luxury, Tyranny, Oppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Popiſh, Sinful, Heatheniſh, Fooliſh, Apeiſh Cuſtoms and Practiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelves, the City, and the reſt of the Nation, attending the ſame, with many other the like wicked actions committed by you, which would be too tedious to mention; wherein alſo you did worſe then the Old Parliament.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Did the <hi>Old Parliament do evilly in not providing ſuch Qualifications in the Act for a New Repreſentative they were about in the time of their firſt Sitting, as to keep out Presbyters, Neuters, and Malignants from coming into Power for the future, and therein would have given away the Cauſe into the hands that never bled for it, and that would impoſe upon their Brethren, which you ſay had you ſuffered, you ſhould have been the worſt people in the world, and have become Traytors both to God and Man.</hi> So did you. And therein (to uſe your own words) were you indeed <hi>Traytors both to God and Man;</hi> for the very next Parliament that was called after your <hi>General</hi> was made <hi>Protector,</hi> and the next to that, did moſt conſiſt of <hi>Presbyters, Neuters,</hi> and <hi>Malignants,</hi> and Perſons packed for the ſupport of your Intereſts, and ſecluded and kept from ſitting near a hundred Members, among whom were ſeveral Perſons for a Commonwealth Intereſt, that ſo they might hot hinder your corrupt deſign of advancing and perpetuating your ſelves. And juſt ſo was it in the laſt Free Parliament (ſo called) ſummoned by his Son <hi>Richard</hi> your late Protector, choſen (as was his Fathers) by the Clergy and<note n="*" place="margin">And this alſo you did contrary to your former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Spirit and Principle in your Speech to the Little Parliament. See Book pag. 42. where you acknowledge that the whole Bulk of the People of this Nation were not fit to chuſe or be choſen Rulers till the Spirit was more poured forth, and they thereby brought to own the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt.</note> ſpirit of the Nation, moſt of whom were enemies to, and oppoſers of the Cauſe of God and his People, and what endeavours you uſed by writing Letters, and ſending your Emiſſaries and Agents to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Burroughs and Corporations to get your Kindred, Relations, Servants, Flatterers, and mercenaries, whether wiſe men or fools, honeſt men or knaves to be choſen for that end, and to keep the faithful friends of the Cauſe from being choſen, (another evil complain'd of in the Old Parliament) and yet how the Lord blaſted you in all your vain hopes and expectations from them, and for the preſervation of your ſelves and the honeſt Intereſt, you were ſtill neceſſitated to diſſolve them you very well know; in all which you not onely dealt deceitfully, treacherouſly, and wickedly with your former honeſt Principles, but doubtleſs did worſe then the Old Parliament would have done; and the great kindneſs you pretended to ſhew unto the good People in diſſolving them, doth not in the leaſt excuſe your great evil in laying ſuch a wicked Foundation as neceſſitated you to call ſuch unworthy Perſons to be building upon it: And I appeal to any honeſt faithful, unbyaſt perſon to judge, whether your late unbelieving, treacherous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, (ſince the ſecond Diſſolution of the Old Parliament) in framing your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:167283:16"/>new Council of Safety (ſo called) moſtly with thoſe very Perſons that were the promoters &amp; abettors of the late Apoſtacy, as alſo caſting ſeveral faithful friends of the Cauſe out of the City Militia, and placing in their ſtead ſuch as Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Tichborn,</hi> Alderman <hi>Pack,</hi> Alderman <hi>Viner,</hi> Alderman <hi>Atkins,</hi> Alderman <hi>Foot,</hi> Alderman <hi>Chiverton,</hi> and others who have likewiſe bowed the knee unto, and abetted the aforeſaid wickedneſs, doth not declare you (notwithſtanding your many late Prayers, Tears, Faſtings, ſhews of Repentance, and alſo Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of your ſincere intentions to return to own and advance the Cauſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt) to be ſtill acted by the very ſame, if not a worſe ſpirit then before.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Did the Old Parliament in their ſecond Sitting ſo carry it, as if <hi>the Intereſt of the People of God was grown cheap with them, and not laid to heart, and diſcountenanced their buſineſs that came before them to the diſcountenancing of them and countenancing the Malignant Party, and as if they never intended good to the people of God.</hi> So did you, and worſe. For you ſtood by and upheld your Old Protector whileſt he confirmed a former wicked Ordinance, and therewith all thoſe curſed, Popiſh, Oppreſſive Laws, contrary to Scripture or Reaſon, for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning the Lords People, taking away their goods, and forcing trebble dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages from them for non-payment of Tythes, and this out of an unbelieving carnal deſign to quiet the National Clergy, and draw them to your Intereſt, though known enemies to the Cauſe of Chriſt which hath been, is, and ought further to be carried on in theſe Nations, whereby ſeveral poor Families of the Lords people have been almoſt ruined and undone; and how they were many times diſcountenanced and overthrown in their buſineſs by reaſon of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and abetting thoſe corrupt Intereſts you very well know.</p>
            <p>Did the Old Parliament do evilly in their late Sitting in keeping Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi> out of <hi>Biſhopſgate</hi> ſo long, and ſo unwillingly voting his readmiſſion at laſt, as alſo in being ſo negligent, and backward in doing right to Mr. <hi>Feake,</hi> in reſtoring him to the Meeting-houſe by <hi>Newgate Market,</hi> where he formerly preached, and was placed by their Order, and afterward unrighteouſly turned out by the late Apoſtacy. As alſo in voting Major General <hi>Harriſon</hi> uncapable of future publick employment? So did you. For after the Old and Little Parliament were diſſolved, you firſt turned Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> out of thoſe places, and caſt them into priſons for their faithfulneſs to the Cauſe of Chriſt, and your forementioned honeſt Principles, and witneſſing againſt your back-ſliding from them, and ſuffered, if not ordered, Mr. <hi>Lee,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and others who are known enemies to the Cauſe to come into their places, and there continued them, keeping the others out, till the late Sitting of the <hi>Old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> who (though long firſt) reſtored Mr. <hi>Sympſon;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Peake</hi> (if there be a keeping cloſe to the former honeſt ſpirit, and orders thereupon) was and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly kept out both by them and you to this very day. And how you likewiſe took Maj. Gen. <hi>Harriſon's</hi> Commiſſion from him, or otherwiſe put him by his Command in the Army, as alſo inhumanely and unworthily ſent him to Priſons and Baniſhment upon the ſame account with the former, and to this very day endeavour all you can to keep him and other faithful friends out of Publick Employment, unleſs they comply with your ſelfiſh corrupt practiſes, and own
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:167283:16"/>you, as indeed returned from your Apoſtacy, when it is not ſo, you very well know; which with many other things of this kinde that might be mentioned, declares plainly that the intereſt of the people of God is grown cheap with you and not laid to heart, and their buſineſs diſcountenanced to the countenance of the Malignant Party, and that you intend good to the people of God no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then your own intereſt and ſafety will ſtand therewith, and therein alſo are worſe then the Old Parliament.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Did the Old Parliament <hi>manifeſt their Spirit and Complexion to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt by their backwardneſs in proceeding to regulate the Law which was then, and to this day is ſo much groaned under, as that many moneths together</hi> (you ſay) <hi>was not ſufficient to paſs over one word called incumberances.</hi> So did you and worſe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees. For when the forementioned honeſt Party of the Little Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had voted a new Body or Moddel of the Law for the ſpeedy ending of Law Suits with little charge, as alſo the aboliſhing and taking away the then and now corrupt oppreſſive Court of Chancery, wherein was depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding twenty three thouſand Cauſes, where ſome had lain five, ſome ten, ſome twenty, ſome thirty years and more, to the undoing of many families; and had appointed a Committee for the bringing of Sir <hi>John Lenthal</hi> Chief Jaylor of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench</hi> Priſon, and all other corrupt perſons imployed in Publick Truſt to an account for the evil management of their Truſt, and had made ſome good progreſs therein, to the ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or caſting the aforeſaid Sir <hi>John Lenthal</hi> out of his place, among other good things they were doing for the eaſe of the people, you turned them out on purpoſe to hinder them from bringing what they had ſo voted, and were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on to do, unto perfection. And after this illegally, and diſhoneſtly impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and baniſhed ſome of the aforeſaid honeſt Members of the Little Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and others of the faithful friends of the Cauſe without any thing laid to their charge, ſeeing the face of an accuſer, or bringing them to a legal Tryal, which is worſe then was done in the Kings dayes. As alſo ſent Alderman <hi>Chiverton</hi> then Lord Major, (now one of your Commiſſioners for the City Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia) and Alderman <hi>Robbinſon</hi> the then Sheriff, two reputed Malignants, with their Malignant City Marſhals the acquaintance and confederates of the late <hi>Mall Cutpurſe</hi> and her Crew, to hale others of the forementioned friends of the Cauſe from their Meeting-place in <hi>Colemanſtreet,</hi> when they were ſeeking the Lord, and pleading for his <hi>Righteous Cauſe,</hi> and witneſſing againſt your Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from it, and to caſt them in priſons to make them give over, and afterward ſet the then Chief Juſtice <hi>Glyn,</hi> one of the <hi>Eleven Members</hi> formerly impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by your ſelves of Treaſon, as alſo Alderman <hi>Tichborne,</hi> and others of your now new <hi>Council of Safety,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Militia,</hi> to try and paſs Sentence upon them, who though the Jury had cleared them, yet to ſatisfie your luſt, and pleaſe you, for their own advantage, they illegally laid Fines upon<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Cornet, Day, <hi>and</hi> John Clark.</note> two of them and kept them in <hi>Newgate</hi> above half a year after at great charges, and when the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and overturning diſpenſations of the Lord came upon you, and took away the <hi>light of your Eyes, breath of your Noſtrils,</hi> and <hi>ſtruck your head from off
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:167283:17"/>your Shoulders,</hi> and they durſt keep them no longer, they turned them out ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing unto them; which wicked action among other things of this kinde that might be mentioned, declares plainly <hi>That the Cauſe even among your ſelves,</hi> (as well as among the <hi>Old Parliament</hi>) was almoſt <hi>in every thing going to the ground, yea the Cauſe of the people of God a deſpiſed thing with you.</hi> Likewiſe unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly decimated the Eſtates of the Cavaleers; when by your carnal, unbelieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſelfiſh <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> they would not be drawn to your Intereſt. As alſo carryed it in ſo inſolent, high, and arbitrary a manner, that almoſt no Lawyer durſt plead in a Cauſe againſt you, for fear of being caſt into priſon; Revived, and upheld Monopolyes (ſo greatly complained of in the late Kings dayes) not onely in Merchandiſe and other things, but alſo upon the Scriptures; ſo that ſome <hi>Bibles</hi> were not to be had without paying ten, or eighteen pence a piece more, then they were formerly ſold for: Suppreſſed the printing Preſſes againſt all who wrote in vindication of that Bleſſed Cauſe, and thoſe good Principles you once ſo highly pretended to own and aſſert, and againſt your <hi>Judas</hi>=like Treachery and Back-ſliding from them, and is another evil that your ſelves formerly<note n="*" place="margin">See Book called the Looking-glaſs, page 19.20.</note> complained of in the Old Parliament. alſo ſtood by, and abetted your <hi>Kingling,</hi> or <hi>Humble Petition and Advice</hi> Parliament; Moſtly made up of Sons, Kindred, Servants, and Sallary-men, to trappan, and like ſo many <hi>evening Wolves,</hi> ravening the prey, cunningly to ſteal upon and take away one whole years rent from the people for all ſuch new houſes as they had built (within ten miles round the City of <hi>London</hi>) upon new Foundations, to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, if not altogether ruine and undoing of many of them, the better to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your new Court Pride, Pomp, and Luxury, which perſons of a ſelf-denying, ſincere, honeſt, publick ſpirit would greatly abhor to do.</p>
            <p>All which, with many other evil practiſes of yours relating to the late and preſent abhord Apoſtacy that might be mentioned, (which I leave to the lately diſſolved Members of the Old Parliament for the leſſening their evil, if compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with yours, to make a more full diſcovery of) it plainly appears, that not onely in every one of thoſe particulars which you have ſo charged upon them as the reaſons of their firſt and ſecond Diſſolution, but alſo then for which you fought with, brought to Juſtice, and beheaded the late King, you have by far done worſe your ſelves, and therein <hi>overpaſſed the deeds of the wicked;</hi> which treacherous dealing of yours with, wickedly departing from, <hi>Judas</hi>-like betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as it were crucifying and keeping down in the grave that bleſſed Cauſe of Chriſt, his faithful people, and thoſe good Principles you once ſo greatly pretended to own, thereby ſtanding in the way, and hindering the faithful Friends of the Cauſe from going to <hi>Zion,</hi> is the chief cauſe of all thoſe loſſes, miſeries, diſappointments, and judgements which hath been from the Lord upon you and the Nation (as upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of old, who would not let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go to <hi>Canaan</hi>) from that time to this very day, and hath occaſioned the enemy both at home and abroad, as alſo the Carnal, Epiſcopal, Atheiſticall Apprentices of the City of <hi>London,</hi> whom the Lord for the malignity and oppoſition of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to his Cauſe and People hath ſo many times diſappointed and ſubdued as the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:167283:17"/>people of his curſe to miſapprehend and ſay, it is onely becauſe the Government by <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> is taken away, (with other blinde ſtuff of that nature) and that it will never be well until they be reſtored again; thereby caſting dirt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as much as in them lies, making null and void all thoſe wonderfull and glorious Appearances, Deliverances, and Victories which the Lord from time to time hath ſhewen and given to his People both againſt them and it; as if all had been onely by Chance, Fortune, or Common Providences, or as among <hi>Papiſts, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> and to threaten once more to put it to the trial whether it be not ſo; and how far the Lord may make uſe of them as his Rod to rebuke and ſcourge you, and all your Cycophant Addreſſors, who have ſided with, abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and not witneſſed againſt your wickedneſs, as alſo the poor Nation may likewiſe ſuffer in the common calamity for your ſakes, together with their own iniquities and oppoſition of their ſpirits to the Cauſe, and People of God; the Lord who will not be mocked nor dealt treacherouſly withal by you, as you have mocked and dealt treacherouſly with his people onely knows; For how can you rationally or honeſtly expect any other but that a conſumption and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the Almighty is determined, and will unavoidably come upon you, unleſs you ſpeedily and thorowly repent and return from your Apoſtacy. And yet too too much is it to be feared, that notwithſtanding this, as alſo all the wholeſome advice, admonition, and reproof, that by ſpeaking, writing, printing, and therein <hi>line upon line,</hi> that from time to time hath in all ſingleneſs and plainneſs been laid before you in order thereunto, you lay it not to heart, nor intend to act according to it no more then the Old Parliament did the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Advice of the ſame nature, which you, ſay you, gave to them, but are ſtill reſolved to deal treacherouſly and deceitfully (as they did) with the Cauſe and People of God, and to go on acting by the very ſame carnall, ſelfiſh ſpirit, and policy as before, calling to your aſſiſtance chiefly thoſe very Perſons that were the firſt Contrivers, Promoters, and Abetters of the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and preſent Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, whom the Lord hath had, and doubtleſs yet hath a controverſie with, and would not, no nor without eminent repentance will not own, nor give favour in the eyes of his faithful People, but rather more cauſe them to ſtink in their noſtrils, and are as unwilling and backward (as a Bear to come to the ſtake) to call the forementioned faithful Perſons turned out of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> and others of that publique ſpirit into Power, for fear they will do their work too thorowly. But go on as long as you will, and be as Politique in your Shifts and Contrivances to uphold your carnal Intereſts, and to keep them out as ever you can, yet aſſure your ſelves the Lord who <hi>loveth righteouſneſs,</hi> and hateth iniquity, and every deceitful practice, and takes the wrong you have done to them, and therein to his Cauſe, as if done unto himſelf, and hath already begun to call you to an account, and to puniſh you for the ſame, will never ceaſe diſappointing, overturning, and ſending ſtreights upon you, till you acknowledge your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that very thing, (and well if you eſcape ſo too) which ſo far as I yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand you have not done to this very day. And that you may the better weigh and conſider what I ſay herein, read the following Scriptures. Iſa. 26.11. <hi>Lord when thy hand is lifted up they will not ſee, but they ſhal ſee, and be aſhamed for their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:167283:18"/>envy at the people, the fire of thine enemies ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> Alſo Iſa. 33.1. <hi>Woe to thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpoiled, and dealeſt treacherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee, when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoil thou ſhalt be ſpoiled, &amp;c.</hi> comp. Rom. 1.31, 32. and Rom. 2.3.</p>
            <p>Think not becauſe you are a profeſſing people, and the Lord hath ſo many times appeared for you, covering your heads in the day of battel, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe given you <hi>houſes full of good things which you filled not,</hi> Deut. 6.11. that you ſhall alwayes have his preſence and ſalvation with, and about you, though you commit iniquity, and go on therein without repentance, but rather conſider what he ſaith to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who had ſinned and back-ſlidden from him as you have done. Amos 3.2. <hi>You onely have I known of all the Families of the Earth, therefore will I puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how greatly hath the bleſſed Name, Cauſe, Wayes, and People of God ſuffered, been reproached, ſet at nought, and blaſphemed by your (as well as by the late <hi>Old Parliaments</hi>) evil mannagement of the Affairs under your hand from the firſt beginning of your Apoſtacy, or turning the honeſt Members left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in the <hi>Little Parliament</hi> out of the Power to this very day? How is the Enemy encouraged to lift up themſelves in the hopes and expectations that they ſhall once more have a day to advance their <hi>Carnal, Popiſh, Superſtitious, wicked</hi> Intereſt, and to tread down the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>People of God</hi> under their feet?</p>
            <p>What might not you have done by this time for the Advancement of the Cauſe of God and his People not onely in our own, but in other Nations, had you kept growing up in the light, ſpirit, and practice of thoſe good Principles you once ſo greatly pretended to own, and had not through unbelief and a ſelf-ſeeking, ſelf-exalting ſpirit ſo treacherouſly and wickedly departed from them? Yea, how far might we have been gotten on of our journney towards <hi>Zion,</hi> had you preſſed forward according to what above nine years ſince you<note n="*" place="margin">See Declar. (Heathen-like called) Auguſt 1. 1650. by it ſelf, or in p. 18, 19. of a Book called the Fifth-Monarchy.</note> declared to the Scots; wherein you ſay, <hi>It is our prayer daily that thoſe that fear the Lord in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>may become one in the hand of the Lord, and joyn together in the Advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and throwing down and trampling upon the Seat of the Beaſt; why ſhould not</hi> Scotland <hi>as well as</hi> England <hi>rejoyce to ſee the Horns of the Beaſt cut off, that we may joyn together to hate the Whore, and burn her fleſh with fire; as alſo that the Lord was about to put on the Saitns beautiful garments, and to make them a praiſe in the Earth.</hi> And likewiſe above ſix years ſince to the <hi>Little Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> page 43, 44, of the forementioned Book, that <hi>you thought ſomething was as the door, that you were at the threſhold, and therefore it became you and them to life up your heads, and to encourage your ſelves in the Lord;</hi> looking upon your ſelves to be either the <hi>Stone</hi> it ſelf, or at leaſt to have had ſomewhat of the ſpirit of it, and that your <hi>Call</hi> of the <hi>Little Parliament</hi> was a fruit and an effect of the <hi>Stones</hi> ſmiting; ſaying, <hi>That ſome of you thought it your duty to endeavour that way, not vainly looking on that Propheſie,</hi> Dan. 2.44. and the Kingdom ſhall not be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to another people, and that <hi>it was ſet upon your hearts, and upon all the faithfull in the Land,</hi> it may be it was not your duty <hi>to deliver it over to any other people, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:167283:18"/>that that Scripture might then be fulfilling unto you.</hi> Alſo that <hi>we were at the edge of the Promiſes and Propheſies, and did think that God was bringing the Jews home to their ſtation, from the Iſles of the Sea, as once he led Iſrael thorow the Red Sea; And although there were neither Promiſe for this or Propheſie, we ſhould be coveting after the beſt things, and therefore if you were to chuſe the meaneſt Officer in the Army, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, you would chuſe a godly man that had Principles, eſpecially where truſt is to be committed, for you knew where to have a man of Principles, and wiſht that all our Magiſtrates were ſo choſen, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein you ſpeak as highly for the <hi>Work, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt of Chriſt,</hi> as can almoſt be ſpoken by any in this, or indeed in any other day on this ſide the eminent fulfilling of the <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Propheſies</hi> relating thereunto.</p>
            <p>Now what great things might have been done towards the <hi>Calling</hi> home of the <hi>Jews?</hi> Alſo what a glorious <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> from the Lord might we have had upon and about us, to the <hi>amazement, terrour,</hi> and <hi>ſilencing</hi> of the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> both at home and abroad, according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. ſo as they would not have dared to lift up their heads, or have wagged their tongues againſt us as now they do. Yea, how many poor creatures might, according to <hi>Eſther</hi> 8.17. <hi>&amp; Zech.</hi> 8.22, 23. have been won over to own and love the Cauſe and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that now are either turn'd <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or elſe remain in the hardneſs, wickedneſs, and oppoſition of their hearts and ſpirits thereunto, had you not declined, but, as was ſaid before, kept growing up in your then light, as alſo in the <hi>frame</hi> of your <hi>ſpirits</hi> and actions towards that perfection that ſhall be in the <hi>Lords faithful People,</hi> when the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Zion ſhall go forth as brightneſs, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof as a lamp that burneth, and he make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 62.1, 6, 7. which is our duty not onely to be praying for, but preſſing after, as well as after that perfection of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>holineſs</hi> in the inward man that ſhall be in that day, or at the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the dead Saints, when our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come, and all the Saints with him,</hi> Zech. 4.5. comp. 1 Cor. 15.23. Rev. 20.4. and how we were growing up into this <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> according to <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.7. began to <hi>return from their oppreſſion, revive as the corn, and grow as the vine,</hi> and this glorious <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> was <hi>dawning</hi> and <hi>breaking</hi> in upon us, when the <hi>honeſt ſpirit</hi> (which you have ſo rejected) was encouraged and acting in the <hi>Authority</hi> of this Nation, as hath been already mentioned, you very well know. But our too ſad experience tells us, that the Lord hath now cauſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to complain and ſay, according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4.21, 22, 23. <hi>Ah ſinful Nation, a people laden with iniquity, a ſeed of evil doers, children that are corrupters, they have forſaken the Lord, they have provoked the Holy One of Iſrael. How is the faithfull City become an Harlot, it was full of judgement, righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now murtherers. Thy ſilver is become droſs, thy wine mixt with water, thy Princes are rebellious and companions of thieves; every one loveth gifts, and followeth after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, they judge not the fatherleſs, neither doth the cauſe of the widdow come unto them;</hi> and upon this account we have cauſe to lament and complain, according to Lam. 2.15, 16. <hi>All our enemies have opened their months againſt us, they hiſs and gnaſh their teeth, they ſay we have ſwallowed them up, certainly this is the day that we looked for, we have found we have ſeen it,</hi> comp. with <hi>Job Chap.</hi> 29. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 30.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:167283:19"/>and this is the very ſtate and condition that the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>people of God,</hi> and the <hi>Nation,</hi> which had once a <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> upon them, is brought into at this day by reaſon of your Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>Now in regard it is thus with you and the poor <hi>Nation</hi> (for your ſakes) as it is, and <hi>things are under ſo ill ſenſe abroad</hi> (to uſe your own words to the <hi>Old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>) <hi>and the iſſue like to be the further diſpleaſure and judgements of the Lord againſt you, the diſſatisfaction and ſadning the hearts of his faithful people, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all things into greater Confuſion, if you continue to ſteer your courſe as formerly;</hi> which ſo far as I can yet ſee, or hear, you are reſolved to do, though the <hi>Cauſe, Your ſelves,</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi> periſh: and although you therein ſo carry it as to give the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>Faithfull People</hi> juſt cauſe to ſay of you, as of <hi>Ephraim</hi> of old, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.17. <hi>The Army is joyned to Idols, let them alone.</hi> Yet conſidering on the other hand, that he likewiſe calls to ſuch a back-ſliding people as you are, to <hi>return unto him:</hi> and upon their <hi>return,</hi> hath graciouſly promiſed he <hi>will heal their back-ſliding, and love them freely, Jer.</hi> 3.22. comp. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. And not knowing though you have gone on ſo long in the hardneſs of your hearts, but he may yet <hi>pour out a ſpirit of grace and ſupplication upon you,</hi> and give you to look upon his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Faithfull Remnant</hi> whom you have ſo rejected, and as it were <hi>Pierced</hi> and <hi>Crucified,</hi> and <hi>to mourn, and be in bitterneſs</hi> for the ſame, <hi>as one is in bitterneſs for his firſt-born:</hi> as alſo to return to the real practice of your forementioned honeſt Principles, <hi>it being better with you then then now;</hi> and to <hi>cauſe Judgement ſo viſibly to return unto Righteouſneſs, as that all the upright in heart may follow it,</hi> and be encouraged to venture their Lives with you as formerly, againſt the Common Enemy, which as things now ſtand they cannot but be very unwilling to do. And likewiſe having, though I have ſo <hi>ſearched to the quick</hi> and <hi>ſpoken plainly,</hi> a deſire to be <hi>merciful, as my heavenly Father is merciful;</hi> and to be inſtrumental, ſo far as he ſhall aſſiſt, to pluck you out of this deep ditch you have plunged your ſelves into; and that <hi>whether you will hear, or whether you will forbear,</hi> you may be left without excuſe. As alſo that I may diſcharge my love and duty towards the Bleſſed <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt, the Saints,</hi> and the Land of my Nativity, I ſhall in all <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> lay before you, what according to my preſent <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> will (if any thing) recover the forementioned <hi>Cauſe, the Saints, Your ſelves,</hi> and this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ruined <hi>Nation</hi> out of that ſad and periſhing condition that by reaſon of your <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and treacherous dealing with your former honeſt principles they are brought into, and will engage the forementioned <hi>Glorious Preſence</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of the Lord to be with, and about us, as in former dayes; in order to which, though in and of my ſelf I am very unworthy and unable to adviſe in a buſineſs of ſo high and weighty a concernment as this is: I <hi>counſel</hi> and <hi>propoſe</hi> as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, endeavour to be humbled for, repent of, and to turn from every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſonal ſin and iniquity that you have been in the committing of, for if you, or I, or any other <hi>regard iniquity in our hearts,</hi> or wilfully live in the practiſe of any known ſin, <hi>the Lord will not hear our prayers,</hi> nor accept of any thing we do for him wherein his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> is concerned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8, 9.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:167283:19"/>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11. to 20. Therefore if there be any ſuch thing as <hi>falſe muſters,</hi> or <hi>Dead pay,</hi> or wherein ſoever wrong hath been done, or ſin committed, do ſo no more; As alſo reſtore back to thoſe of whom you have bought <hi>Debenters</hi> at cheap rates, ſomewhat proportionable to your great gains thereby, if they be living; and if dead, then to the <hi>Widdows, Children,</hi> or <hi>Kindred</hi> related to them that are left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them: As alſo to be ſure to promiſe nothing to any for the future either of a <hi>publick or private nature,</hi> but what is in the power of your hand to do, and have a real intention thorowly and ſpeedily to perform, and herein be growing up into that <hi>holy frame</hi> mentioned Zeph. 3.13. <hi>The Remnant of Iſrael ſhall not do iniquity, nor ſpeak lies, neither ſhall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouths, &amp;c.</hi> And what I ſay to you in this particular, I ſay to my ſelf, and to all others fearing the Lord; for the People whom the Lord will delight to <hi>uſe</hi> in his <hi>Work,</hi> muſt be a ſincere, upright, ſelf-denying, holy people, therefore let us not hide our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, but rather ſay to the Lord according to Job 34.32. <hi>That which I ſee not teach thou me, if I have done iniquity, I will do no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Be alſo humbled for, repent of ſuppreſs, and put away for the time to come, All the Pride of Apparel, &amp;c. Luxury, Gaming, and whatever elſe is ſinful, and of an evil report that is committed in your Families, by your ſelves, Wives, Children, Servants, and Relations, according to Job 11.13, 14. comp. with Chap. 22.23. <hi>If thou prepare thine heart, and ſtretch out thine hand towards him, if iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be in thy hand, put it far away, and let not wickedneſs dwell in thy tabernacles, &amp;c.</hi> And endeavour all you can for the future to get ſuch as fear the Lord to attend upon you; for it is not onely your duty, but declared Principle to the Little Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſo to do. See page 43. of the forementioned Book; Let not their failings, infirmities, and too many times neglect of duty, hinder you from doing yours, if you can get them; there is little good to be expected from you whoever you are, though your knowledge and profeſſion be never ſo high, whileſt you are careleſs and ſlight in this particular.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Be alſo deeply humbled for, and repent of your forementioned great Apoſtacy from, rejecting of, &amp; treacherous dealing with the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt, and your forementioned honeſt Principles, and all your perſecuting, Impriſoning, and Baniſhing of your Brethren for their faithfulneſs thereunto, and for all other your great evils and miſcarriages therein committed, whereby the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath been, and is ſo much reproached and diſhonoured, and his <hi>Bleſſed Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> ſo greatly ſtopped and hindered, The hearts of his faithful people grieved, and hath brought ſo much poverty and miſery upon this Nation, and return in the ſincerity and uprightneſs of your hearts to revive and promote the aforeſaid <hi>Bleſſed Cauſe,</hi> and thoſe good Principles from whence you have ſo greatly departed, and reſolve in the ſtrength of the Lord to <hi>return no more to folly.</hi> And that this your repentance and thorow returning may ſo appear to all the faithful Friends of the Cauſe, as to put them paſt all doubts and fears of your deceiving them any more for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Caſt off the Counſel of <hi>St. Johns, Liſle, Whitlock, Philip Nye, Tho. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win, Dean Owen,</hi> (ſo called) (and all other the like Incendaries) the <hi>Heads</hi> of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:167283:20"/>corrupt <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> unleſs you finde they have really and thorowly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their great evil in being ſo inſtrumental to help turn, (and keep) your then General and you aſide into theſe crooked paths after the firſt Diſſolution of the Old, and choice, and turning out of the <hi>Little Parliament;</hi> as alſo ſee them ſingly and ſincerely preſſing you to come up to the practiſe of your former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and to the owning of that ſpirit, thoſe principles and perſons which you once ſo greatly ſeemed to own, but afterwards through the enmity of your ſpirits, and their wicked Counſel and Advice as greatly and wickedly rejected. For if they remain as they were, <hi>Owen,</hi> &amp;c. according to <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.14. Are the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that have ſeen vain and fooliſh things for you, and have not diſcovered your iniquity to turn away the judgements that are fallen upon you, but have and do ſee for you falſe burthens and cauſes of baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Send by way of intreaty (it being your duty ſo to do,) according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.24.25.) having ſo greatly wronged them) for thoſe faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom you have ſo rejected and turned out of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> whoſe Garments have not ſince been defiled with the late, and preſent <hi>Apostacy,</hi> or if they have, are known to have throughly repented of the ſame, with others of that publick ſpirit to come unto you, who if any in the Nation, yea, I may ſay in the world will (the Lord aſſiſting) bring forth the good things promiſed, and have been ſo long expected for the good of the Nation. And when you have ſo done.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Acknowledge your great ſin and iniquity to them. Firſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting and caſting them out of your hearts, and afterwards out of that <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> on purpoſe to hinder them from doing that good for the people, which you pretendedly diſſolved the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> for not doing of, and called them to do; which were no other then what you will finde the true <hi>friends of the Cauſe,</hi> will neither give you, nor any other that for the future may come into the <hi>Government</hi> of the Nation reſt, do what you can to uphold your own and other carnal Intereſts, in oppoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, yea the Lord no reſt till they do obtain; And when you have in the ſingle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs of your hearts, thus acknowledged your iniquity to them and deſired mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for the ſame, (as <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.16. to 20. <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren did to him.) I hope they will have ſo much both of the ſpirit of the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> though brought to your <hi>Husks,</hi> and of the ſpirit of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his Brethren, as to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go forth in their ſpirits to meet this in you, and weepingly to joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over you, as alſo to pardon and paſs by all the wrongs and injuries, that you have done unto them, and therein to the Cauſe of God and his people. But if this be not in your hearts to do, they muſt remain where they are, keeping the ſame diſtance from you as before, leſt they go before they are ſent, and ſo come off with loſs and diſappointments in their own ſpirits as to you, as my ſelf and others have done ſince you ſo deceivingly Declared that <hi>you were now as ever equally endeared to the good Old Cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. when it was not ſo.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, With the <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> of the faithfull friends of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> both in <hi>City</hi> and Countrey (it being uſurpation in you and acting arbitrarily to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:167283:20"/>do any thing without them) Deliver up (with limitations not to impoſe upon the conſciences of any in matters of Faith and Worſhip, and in all things elſe that are againſt the ſafety of the Whole) the Power, Authority, and Government of the Nation into their hands; for (by what hath been ſaid both by you, my ſelf, and others in this and other Papers, and keeping cloſe to the ſpirit of them) under Chriſt their right it is, and take heed of mixing them as in the time of their firſt Sitting with perſons of a contrary ſpirit and principle, on purpoſe to hinder them from doing the good they are called to do, and thereby deſignedly and wickedly give your ſelves a ſecond feigned neceſſity of turning them out and ſetting up another <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Protector</hi> upon their ruines as you did before, but rather encourage and ſtrengthen them all you can in the bringing forth this good, and ſuppreſſing the evil; for that it is onely the bringing forth of righteouſneſs, and breaking off all yokes of oppreſſion, that will ſave and exalt this ſinking Nation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.17. to 20.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe perſons thus called together, having more light, faith, and communion with God then formerly they had, in the work of the latter dayes, and that they are called unto, as I conceive they have, and laying <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Foundation</hi> on which they intend to <hi>Build;</hi> as alſo conſulting with and managing all their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs according to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as is their judgement founded upon the ſame, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and not onely theirs, but of moſt of the <hi>Friends</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as alſo aſſented to by your ſelves, and all the <hi>Great Lawyers,</hi> and all others preſent at the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Widdrington <hi>having preſented your Protector with a Robe, afterwards delivered him a Bible, and among other expreſſions ſaid,</hi> It is a Book of Books, and beſides other things it conteins in it both Precepts and Examples for good Government. <hi>Alexander</hi> ſo highly valued the Books of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and other great Princes other Books, that they have laid them every night under their Pillows; theſe are all but Legends and Romances to this one Book, a Book to be had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in remembrance; I finde it ſaid in part of this Book which I ſhall deſire to read, and it is this, <hi>Deut 17.18, 19, 20.</hi> And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write a Copy of this Law in a Book out of that which is before the Prieſtt, and Levites, and it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the dayes of his life, that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, and to keep all the words of this Law, and thoſe ſtatutes to do them, that his heart be not lifted up above his Brothren, and that he turn not aſide from the Commandment to the right hand or to the left, to the end he may prolong his dayes in his Kingdom, he and his Children in the midſt of Iſrael. <hi>In which words you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Scriptures ought to be the foundation of both the Government and Laws of this Nation, which, though after this, you decline from, and therein adde</hi> Apoſtacy <hi>to</hi> Apoſtacy, <hi>yet do juſtifie all others that ſhall go on therein, and proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture Quualifications for the choice of Rulers, according to</hi> Exod. <hi>18.21.</hi> Hoſea <hi>11.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Speech</hi> made by Sir <hi>Thomas Widdrington</hi> then <hi>Speaker</hi> of your <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> Parliament, at the <hi>ſecond Inauguration</hi> of your late <hi>General</hi> in the <hi>Protectorall Government</hi>) is the duty of all <hi>Gods Magiſtrates</hi> to do, Having alſo the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and welfare of the Nation upon their hearts more then their own, will I hope whileſt they are <hi>Sitting,</hi> carry it ſo <hi>ſelf-denyingly, graciouſly,</hi> and <hi>uprightly,</hi> and with ſuch tenderneſs towards all fearing the Lord, eſteeming none becauſe of this or that judgement, further then their ſincerity and faithfulneſs to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> appears;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:167283:21"/>and will endeavour to do all things both at home and in other Nations ſo for the honour of him who is their and our <hi>Judge, King,</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> as alſo <hi>your own</hi> and the <hi>Nations</hi> real good; and likewiſe with the approbation and conſent of the <hi>faithful Friends</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to carefully provide for the future well <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> by the hands of other faithfull Perſons againſt they riſe, as you will have no occaſion (if your hearts be ſincere and upright with God indeed, and have grace to deny your ſelves) to maintain any enmity in your ſpirits towards them, ſo as to <hi>deſpiſe, reject,</hi> and <hi>turn them out</hi> as you did before, but will rather encourage, rejoyce in, and bleſs God for them. And whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your politique ſhifts and devices may be to avoid it, hither you muſt come at laſt; for without this be done, let the foundation you lay as to future Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and the Perſons you call to build thereon in the outward appearance be never ſo pure, or ſo much for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet it is (and you will finde it ſo) but a <hi>falſe Conception, a Bed too ſhort, a Covering too narrow, a Plaiſter,</hi> that though it may skin over, will not thorowly heal the wound that your <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous dealing with your Principles hath made upon you; for the firſt, foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, Cauſe of the Lords diſpleaſure againſt you muſt be taken away, or elſe no ſound cure can be expected; (neither indeed would ſuch as are faithful, had they a true underſtanding of things, and did ſeriouſly weigh and conſider what hath been already, and might further be ſaid in this buſineſs, dare to come in and aſſiſt you till this work were done, for fear leſt the Houſe that in the ſimplicity of their hearts they would be building, ſhould fall upon their heads); and the Lords thus dealing with you is no other then according to the uſual method he goes in in matters of this nature, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>He that covereth his ſin ſhall not proſper, but he that confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſin ſhall have mercy.</hi> Remember what became of <hi>Cain</hi> who retain'd his wicked ſpirit after he ſlew his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> Gen. 4. to verſe 14. Of the <hi>Ongregation of Iſrael,</hi> who out of ſuch a ſpirit as you are act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by, would have ſtoned <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> for oppoſing their going back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and preſſing them to go on the <hi>Canaan,</hi> Numb. 14.23.32.43. Of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and the two hundred and fifty <hi>famous renowned Princes</hi> of the Congregation, and the people joyning with them in oppoſing the ſpirit of the Lord in <hi>Moſes and Aaron</hi> upon the account with the former, and how all theſe remaining in the wickedneſs of their ſpirits, in oppoſition to the ſpirit of the work of the Lord in his little Remnant in that day muſt not proſper, but their <hi>Carkaſſes fall in the wilderneſs, dye of the Plague, fall before their enemy;</hi> the ground open and ſwallow <hi>Korah</hi> and his company up alive. <hi>Numbers</hi> 16.2.31, 32. <hi>Joſephs Brethren,</hi> who out of the wickedneſs and enmity of their ſpirits towards him, cunningly endeavoured all they could to make him away, and ſold him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> muſt lay aſide their enmity, and own and acknowledge their iniquity therein to him, and beg pardon for the ſame, or elſe no peace or proſperity for them could be expected, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.17. to 21. <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> having <hi>committed whoredom, Begot ſtrange Children, Revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from,</hi> and <hi>Dealt treacherouſly againſt the Lord</hi> as you have done, and the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rebuked them and threatned that they ſhould fall in their iniquity, &amp; that he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:167283:21"/>would be as a <hi>moth and rottenneſs to them,</hi> as he hath hitherto been to you, yet they went on, and the Text ſayes, would not <hi>frame their doings to turn unto their God, becauſe the ſpirit of whoredoms was in the midſt of them,</hi> as it is with you; but inſtead of returning to the Lord in a right manner, as to the very thing wherein they had diſpleaſed him. It is ſaid, <hi>When Ephraim ſaw his ſickneſs, and Judah ſaw his wound, then went Ephraim to the Aſſyrian, and ſent to King Jareb,</hi> as you have done to the <hi>Lawyers, National Clergy, Cardinal Mazarine,</hi> and other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Intereſts in the Nation; and it is to be fear'd, that to pleaſe, and keep the rude multitude quiet, that ſo you may go on in your way, or to draw trade to the City, you ſuffer wicked Stage-Playes which were once ſuppreſt to be in uſe again; if a right ſpirit of Magiſtracy were among you, theſe things would not date to ſhew themſelves; but theſe practiſes will not cure you of your wound no more then King <hi>Jareb</hi> and the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> cured them. <hi>For I will be unto Ephraim as a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as a young lion to the Houſe of Judah, even I will tear and go away, I will take away and none ſhall reſcue him; I will go and return to my place till they acknowledge their offence, and ſeek my face, in their affliction they will ſeek me early,</hi> Hoſea 5. Theſe with many other Scriptures of this nature doth witneſs the truth of what hath been aſſerted, wherefore it concerns you to conſider, and to look about you.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, And if yet the Lord ſhall ſo far love, own, and honour you as to change your ſpirits, and cauſe you willingly to ſtoop to this; then their, and your next work, (and oh that it were ſo now) is to endeavour all you can, according to your former declared principles, (denying your ſelves in your kindred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations) if not rightly qualified) to let no man paſs into any command or place of truſt in the <hi>Army, Navy,</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> but faithfull perſons, <hi>fearing God,</hi> and of <hi>approved integrity, and have love to all the Saints;</hi> that ſo wickedneſs may be ſuppreſt, and puniſhed, righteouſneſs encouraged, and the Lord engaged to be preſent with, bleſs, and proſper you in all your future undertakings for the preſervation and advancement of his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>people</hi> as in former dayes. Your thus maintaining purity, love, and unity between perſons both in the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Military Power,</hi> and being as it were of one heart and ſoul upon the account of righteouſneſs, and in a ſpirit of ſelf-denyal, meekneſs and zeal growing up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in every day and generation in the <hi>light, ſpirit</hi> and <hi>things</hi> relating to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the world, towards the forementioned perfection that ſhall be in the Saints in the latter dayes, according to <hi>Micah</hi> 4.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.1, 2. will ſo revive the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and encourage the former honeſt lively ſpirit that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be among you, and through grace is yet alive in a <hi>Little Remnant</hi> (<hi>or elſe we had been as</hi> Sodom) as will not onely cauſe the Lord to be in the midſt of us, but alſo to <hi>rejoyce over us with joy, and ſinging, and to reſt in his love,</hi> as he will more eminently do over his <hi>faithfull people</hi> in the <hi>latter dayes, Zeph.</hi> 3.17. and cauſe our terrour upon our enemies to be greater then ever it was before; and ſurely honeſt men may think it is high time for you who have power in your hands, and profeſs to be Saints, and to be <hi>now as ever equally endeared to the good Old Cauſe,</hi> throughly to deny your ſelves, and not ſuffer the Cauſe, and the Nation to be loſt and ruined for want of a little honeſty; but rather to be doing what
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:167283:22"/>you poſſibly can do to bring things into the poſture that hath been laid before you, for that it ſo plainly appears both by the Scriptures and the late Revolutions and outgoings of the Lord in the midſt of us, together with the preſent fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that hath poſſeſt you, and according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. ſhall more eminently fall upon the Sinners and Hypocrites that pretend to be of <hi>Zion</hi> in the latter dayes; there is nothing leſs then your hearkening unto and following the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned counſel that hath been given you, will ſave you and the Nation from the further ruine and deſtruction that is coming upon you.</p>
            <p>And for your encouragement that the Lord will receive you graciouſly, and paſs by all that you have done againſt him in caſe it be in the purpoſe of your hearts in reality thus to come unto him; conſider that he ſtiles himſelf, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long-ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth, keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin, and will by no means clear the guilty, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 34.6, 7. Alſo the caſe of the Prodigal who went from his Father, and came not again till all was ſpent, and he brought to eat husks, and ſo muſt return or periſh, as ſoon as ever it was in his heart (and accordingly did ſo) to ariſe and go to his Father, and acknowledge his ſin unto him, the Text ſayes, Luke 15.20. <hi>But when he was yet a great way off, his father ſaw him and had compaſſion, and run and fell on his neck and kiſſed him,</hi> and inſtead of upbraiding and puniſhing him, commands the beſt <hi>Robe be put on him, a gold Ring on his hand, and ſhooes on his feet, as alſo the fatted Calf to be killed to eat, drink, and be merry;</hi> and if you return as he did, I hope you will finde no elder Brethren to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at it. And ſo <hi>David</hi> Pſal. 32.3, 4, 5, 6. Sayes he, <hi>When I kept ſilence my bones wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed old through my roaring all the day long, for day and night thy hand was heavy upon me, my moiſture was turn'd into the drought of ſummer: I acknowledged my ſin unto thee, and mine iniquity have I not hid.</hi> Now this is that I minde, ſayes he, <hi>I ſaid</hi> I will confeſs <hi>my tranſgreſſion unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin; for this ſhall every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thou mayeſt be found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren acknowledged the evil they did unto him, and begged pardon for the ſame, inſtead of being revenged upon them, it is ſaid, <hi>And Joſeph wept when they ſpake unto him,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Fear you not, I will nouriſh you and your little ones, and he comforted them, and ſpake kindely to them,</hi> Gen. 50.17, 21. Now if there be ſo much pitty and compaſſion in men to thoſe that treſpaſs againſt them, there is ſo in the Lord much more. Alſo Jer. 3.22. and Hoſea 14 4.5, 6, 7. <hi>I will heal their back-ſlidings, I will love them freely, for mine anger is turned away from him; I will be as the dew unto Iſrael, he ſhall grow as the Lilly, his Branches ſhall ſpread, and his beauty ſhall be as the Olive-tree, and his ſmell as Lebanon; They that dwell under his ſhaddow ſhall return, revive as the corn, and grow as the vine, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe among other Scriptures ſhews the readineſs that is in the Lord to forgive the iniquities of, and to be gracious to a repenting, returning, and back-ſliding people, and oh that this goodneſs of his might powerfully and kindely work upon your hearts to acknowledge your iniquity, deny your ſelf-intereſts, and to return unto him.</p>
            <p>But if notwithſtanding all that I have ſaid (I truſt) in faithfulneſs to the Lord and you, you ſhall yet continue to go on in the hardneſs, wichedneſs, and ſlaviſh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:167283:22"/>fearfulneſs of your hearts and ſpirits, and through the advice and perſwaſion of <hi>Philip Nye, Tho. Goodwin, Dean Owen,</hi> (ſo called) and the forementioned Ineendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon carnal politique conſiderations, be ſtill upholding carnal Intereſts, and the Old, Corrupt Oppreſſive Cuſtoms and Practiſes relating either to Magiſtracy or Miniſtery that hath no warrant in Scripture, which hath brought all the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, confuſion, and miſeries upon the Nation, and the better to carry on this your wicked deſign ſhall continue in your rejecting the true ſpirit of your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned honeſt Principles in thoſe faithfull Perſons turn'd out of the <hi>Little Parliament,</hi> and in others with them, who (as was ſaid before) are ſpirited, and principled, if any, to bring forth good to the Nation; and ſhall rather proceed to moddel your future <hi>Councels</hi> with <hi>Malignants, Neuters, Presbyters,</hi> or uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Apoſtate Protectorians,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Tichbern, Lawrence, Strickland, Whitleck, Clark,</hi> and others of that ſpirit, be it known unto you, you are <hi>Apoſtates</hi> ſtill, though the form you come under in the outward appearance be never ſo ſpecious, and the <hi>Proteſtations</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> you make and ſet forth be never ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and taking upon the people; and the <hi>faithful Friends of the Cauſe,</hi> if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to retain their former integrity and faithfulneſs both to the Lord, and it, cannot, dare not own or touch with you, but according to <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.21.26. muſt <hi>ſeparate</hi> and ſtand at a diſtance from you as before, <hi>leſt they be conſumed in all your ſins.</hi> And although by your more refined Machevilian Devices, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> yea <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>Churches</hi> you may gain thereby to your Intereſt, as alſo by the ſtrength of your <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Navies,</hi> you may think to bear up, and to ſtout it out a little longer againſt the Lord, his Cauſe, and his <hi>faithful Remnant,</hi> and the very ſpirit of your former honeſt Principles, yet know that when you have done all you poſſibly can do to uphold your ſelves therein, the ſpirit of the Lord in his forementioned <hi>faithful Remnant,</hi> as it hath already begun to do, will according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.17. further <hi>overflow,</hi> and look into your <hi>hidling place,</hi> and ſee your ſin as if <hi>written in your foreheads,</hi> and to have a <hi>lye in your right hand,</hi> and ſo will go on to abhor and blow upon you, and by degrees will bring you down, as your <hi>old</hi> and <hi>late Protectors</hi> with their <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and the late <hi>Old Parliament,</hi> and ſo ſhall you become as a <hi>ſhameful ſpewing,</hi> a <hi>by-word,</hi> and a <hi>reproach</hi> not onely in our own, but the Nations round about us. If <hi>God</hi> be <hi>God,</hi> as ſurely he is, and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> be <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of his <hi>Bleſſed Spirit,</hi> and he ever had a <hi>glorious Cauſe</hi> on foot in <hi>England,</hi> leading us out of <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Bondage</hi> towards that glorious <hi>freedom and liberty</hi> that <hi>the Saints who have the firſt fruits of the Spirit, and the whole creation groans, travelleth in pain for,</hi> and <hi>waits</hi> to be delivered into, and ſhall eminently be when <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall fully be delivered, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> deſtroyed, <hi>the Jews</hi> called, and our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> according to Iſa. 32.1, 2. <hi>ſhall Reign and Rule in Righteouſneſs</hi> in the world, all which, as is mentioned in pag. 2. of this Book ſhall certainly be fulfilled in the latter dayes; it muſt be ſo, unleſs the Lord be more merciful to you then ordinarily he is to others that have ſinned againſt, and back-ſlidden from him as you have done, which you have no reaſon to expect, he being ſo much concern'd for the recovery of his Name and Glory to do ſome eminent remarkable thing againſt ſuch a perfidious, hypocritically,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:167283:23"/>Apoſtate profeſſing Generation as you have been and are, that thereby he not onely may keep the feet of his faithful witneſs-bearing people from ſlipping, and encourage them <hi>to fear</hi> and <hi>truſt in him</hi> for the future, but that alſo all others <hi>may hear and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> may not have the leaſt encouragement from what I have ſaid to believe that now all ſhall be their own, and that the Lords lifted up hand againſt you is in order thereunto. I further declare my preſent apprehenſions are, that although the Lord may make uſe of them as his <hi>Rod</hi> to rebuke and ſcourge you not onely for not bringing forth that good, but alſo contrary to your <hi>Declarations</hi> doing worſe things your ſelves, then for which you <hi>ſought with,</hi> and <hi>beheaded</hi> their <hi>King,</hi> as alſo caſt out and baniſhed his Poſterity; yet the Lord hath a people in this Nation whom he hitherto hath kept; and I truſt will keep faithful to the end to his <hi>Bleſsed Cauſe</hi> and thoſe <hi>good Principles</hi> you have ſo treacherouſly departed from, whom he will by his Almighty Power and Providence ſo preſerve out of their hands, that they ſhall never be able to overcome or have their wills upon them, but they ſhall go on in the power <hi>of his Spirit,</hi> (Iſa. 59 19. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2, 3.) with life, power, and an undaunted ſpirit in that bleſſed <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> that for ſome years together hath with ſuch wonderful ſucceſs been carried on againſt them. Neither do I ſee in the midſt of all the confuſions, diſtractions, fears, and ſtraits you are encompaſſed with, the leaſt ground to believe that the Lord will caſt away the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of his <hi>Son,</hi> to make way for a carnal Man, and that wicked Generation whom he hath ſo many times ſubdued as the <hi>people of his Curſe</hi> to bear Rule in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and therein ſend us back to <hi>Egypt</hi> or <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> any more, but rather is thereby removing that which ſtands in the way, and hinders his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people from going to <hi>Zion.</hi> Wherefore if the Lord hath ſo puniſht you a <hi>profeſſing People,</hi> who in the outward ſhew may be ſaid to be the <hi>green tree,</hi> and cauſed you thus to fall before the ſpirit of his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>faithful people;</hi> and ſo to diſappoint and bring to nought all that you contrive and act againſt them; then how ſhall they who are a <hi>wicked Generation,</hi> who ſhould they proſper would <hi>ſet up wickedneſs by a Law,</hi> and may truly be termed the <hi>dry tree,</hi> be able to prevail againſt them? And if you who by your profeſſion are called a righteous people, ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall they who may be ſaid to be <hi>the ungodly and ſinners appear;</hi> The preſent diſpenſations that are upon you, gives not the leaſt ground to believe that they ſhall bear rule any more; therefore let them ſet their hearts at reſt; Surely the Lord would never give his people that light, faith, and communion with himſelf, and ſuch taſtes of ſweetneſs in their ſpirits in that Communion in the diſcovery (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.17, 18.) of the glory that according to the Promiſes and Propheſies is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the latter dayes, and ſo much love to his <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> that hath been formerly, and is yet on foot, though not ſo viſible as once it was, leading thereunto, and ſo owned their Teſtimony againſt you, in bringing you down for oppoſing of them, or ſhewen us all theſe things as the wife of <hi>Manoah</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Judges</hi> 13.23. if he intended to caſt them away, or deliver them up either into your or the common enemies hand. Would the Lord who ſtiles himſelf a <hi>faithfull promiſe, Covenant keeping God, and that cannot lye,</hi> ever bid his people, Iſa. 62.6, 7. <hi>not to keep ſilence and give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh and make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the earth,</hi> if he did not really intend to do ſo? or have begun to put on the <hi>Saints Beautiful Garments, and to make them a praiſe in the earth,</hi> not for their <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> but for his <hi>own Names ſake;</hi> As alſo <hi>plagued Iſrael of Old</hi> for not preſſing forward, but endeavouring to go back to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and will not he who hath a fulneſs of the ſpirit, and love to his work, and all power in his hand to do it, and hath already laid the <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Zions welfare,</hi> carry it on and lay the top-ſtone alſo? Surely he will; And the Rage and Tumults of the Carnal Apprentices and others at this day, for the bringing in <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>They will loſe their lives every one</hi> of <hi>them, rather then they will have ſuch men to Rule as will take away the</hi> corrupt <hi>Cuſtoms and Practices that are among them,</hi> is an eminent hint to me, that the very Day of the ſetting <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints upon his holy Hill of Zion</hi> is at hand, yea ſo upon us, that none can put it off; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo fully ſatisfied in my Spirit it is ſo, I ſhall conclude with the following Scriptures. <hi>Eſther</hi> 6.13. <hi>And Zereſh Hamans wife, and his wiſe-men, ſaid unto him, If Mordecai be of the ſeed of the Jews, before whom thou haſt begun to fall, thou ſhalt not prevail againſt him, but ſhalt ſurely fall before him.</hi> Pſal. 2. <hi>Why do the Heathen rage, and the People imagine a vain thing. The Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, Let us break their Bonds aſſunder, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:167283:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
